<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The dead speaking, or, The living names of two deceased ministers of Christ (contemporary, and eminently usefull in the west of England) viz. Mr. Sam. Oliver, and Mr. Samuel Crook Containing the sermon at the funeralls of the one preached by John Chetwind, B.D. and two severall speeches delivered at the funeralls of them both by William Thomas, B.D. Joyned together at the desire, and for the use chiefly of those Christians who were often occasional partakers of their labours.</title>
            <author>Chetwynd, John, 1623-1692.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 180 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79459</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C3795</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E726_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206780</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896895</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896895</idno>
            <idno type="VID">135400</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79459)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 135400)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2458:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The dead speaking, or, The living names of two deceased ministers of Christ (contemporary, and eminently usefull in the west of England) viz. Mr. Sam. Oliver, and Mr. Samuel Crook Containing the sermon at the funeralls of the one preached by John Chetwind, B.D. and two severall speeches delivered at the funeralls of them both by William Thomas, B.D. Joyned together at the desire, and for the use chiefly of those Christians who were often occasional partakers of their labours.</title>
                  <author>Chetwynd, John, 1623-1692.</author>
                  <author>Thomas, William, 1593-1667. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 75, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by T.W. for John Place, and are to be sold at his shop at Furnivals Inn Gate in Holburn,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653. [i.e. 1654]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Jan: 13".</note>
                  <note>Year is given according to Lady Day dating.</note>
                  <note>"An exhortation immediatly following the sermon that was preached at the funeral of Mr. Samuel Oliver ..." has separate dated title page; pagination and register are continuous.</note>
                  <note>"Another exhortation delivered Jan. 3. 1649. ..." has separate dated title page; pagination and register are continuous.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library, Washington, D.C..</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Oliver, Samuel, b. 1599 or 1600 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Crook, Samuel, 1575-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:135400:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:135400:1"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THE DEAD SPEAKING,</hi> OR, THE LIVING NAMES OF TWO DECEASED MINISTERS OF CHRIST (CONTEMPORARY, And eminently uſefull in the Weſt of England) Viz. <hi>Mr. Sam. Oliver,</hi> and <hi>Mr. Samuel Crook.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Containing the Sermon at the Funeralls of the one Preached by <hi>John Chetwind, B. D.</hi> and two ſeverall Speeches delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at the Funeralls of them both by <hi>William Thomas, B. D.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Joyned together at the deſire, and for the uſe chiefly of thoſe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians who were often occaſional partakers of their labours.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Revel.</hi> 14. 13.</bibl> And I heard a voice from heaven, ſaying unto me, Write, Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are the dead which dy in the Lord, from henceforth, yea ſaith the Spirit, that they may reſt from their labours and their works do follow them.</q>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Perfuncti obedientiae munere per adventum mortis, angelica eos immortalitas, &amp; aeternitas ſequetur beata.</hi> 
                     <bibl>Auguſtine.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. W.</hi> for <hi>John Place,</hi> and are to be Sold at his Shop at Furnivals Inn Gate in <hi>Holburn.</hi> 1653.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:135400:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:135400:2"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>To the Honorable the Lady</hi> Jane Pile <hi>of</hi> Coling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne, <hi>in the County of</hi> Wilts, <hi>The Lady</hi> Cecylia Knollis <hi>of</hi> Reading <hi>in the County of</hi> Berks, <hi>and to the Worſhipful</hi> John Hipſſey <hi>of</hi> Emborough, <hi>and</hi> John Buchland <hi>of</hi> Weſt-Harperay <hi>in the County of</hi> Somerſet <hi>Eſquires, and their Vertuous Conſorts.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Much and Worthy Honored,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O prefix much before ſo little, would be like the making of a wide Gate to a narrow houſe; To ſay nothing, may ſeem (at leaſt in us to whom the care of thoſe is commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted whom your Chriſtian love hath received) to ſavour of ſome ingratitude; and we are ſure is unſuitable to our purpoſe in publiſhing theſe ſhort, and ſuddenly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Notes, which by the deſires of others are drawn from us; wherein our intent is not onely to remember, and preſent as exemplary, the piety of thoſe that are dead, but to tender therewith a juſt acknowlegement of the charitie of thoſe that are living, and your ſelves in particular who have therein the principal part; yet may we not forget divers others (though we name them not) by whoſe ready ſupplies and concurrence, this work of love is more comfortably and fully carried on. We bleſs God both for you and them, well knowing how ſad a thing that is, which (with due reſpect to others of a different judgment) we conceive to be the caſe and curſe <hi>[a]</hi> of <hi>Edom (Jer.</hi> 49. 10, 11. <note n="(b)" place="margin">Vide Vatabli an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not. in loc. Item Oeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lampad. in loc. Ex cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de Superſtes non erit qui te ſau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium et ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huc ſpiran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ſoletur ac dicat, Animo ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro mihi li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beros tuos relinque, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quidem me illis altorem &amp; paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuo. Sic Tremel. &amp; Jun. in locum: Et calvin. in eundem ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum licet ſub diverſa notione.</note>) unto whom the Lord denounceth ſo great, ſo grievous, ſo general a
<pb facs="tcp:135400:3"/> deſtruction and deſolation, that there ſhall not be any left to ſay to the dying Fathers, and Husbands, <hi>Leave thy fatherleſs Children</hi> to my care; <hi>I will preſerve them alive</hi> and nouriſh them, as <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 45. 5, 7, 11. <hi>and let thy Widowes truſt in me,</hi> or, let them reſt on me for taking care of them (as <hi>Prov.</hi> 31. 11.) This lies heavy on the tender hearts of expiring parents. Suitable hereunto are our Saviours words, who when he ment to ſay, He would not leave his Diſciples comfortleſs, but ſend them a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter, expreſſeth it thus, <hi>I will not leave you orphans (John.</hi> 14. 18.) importing, that to be left Orphans, and to be left comfortleſs, is all one. But God leaves not thoſe that are his Orphans. <hi>The righteous are not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken</hi> in themſelves or their ſeed <note n="[a]" place="margin">Pſal. 37. 25.</note> with God (by ſuch Inſtruments as he thinks fit to raiſe) the <hi>fatherleſs find mercy</hi> 
                     <note n="[b]" place="margin">Hoſ. 24. 3.</note> &amp; the Motherles, pity <note n="(c)" place="margin">Pſal. 27. 10. Iſa. 49. 15.</note>. What's a Father but his bowels? <hi>(Iſa.</hi> 63. 16.) What's a Mother but her yernings? 1 <hi>King.</hi> 3. 16.) If God ſtir up thoſe affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to Orphans in ſurviving friends, that's all one as to <note n="[a]" place="margin">Pſal. 109. 12. Lament. 5. 3.</note> form and create new Fathers and Mothers. Theſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſions, Divine providence might ſeeme to intend to draw forth in the preſent caſe, by taking away both the Parents at once; which, though a ſad and unuſual ſtroke in it ſelf, yet is in this comfortable, that it hath made the grace of God in your ſelves and others the more conſpicuous; for we are not willing to look upon your favourable ſupport meerly as a <hi>Gift</hi> (that we may ſpeak in the Apoſtles language, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4. 17.) but eſpecially as a <hi>fruit,</hi> while the tree that gives ſhade and ſuccour to others, ſprings and ſpreads forth it ſelf from a root of grace in you: whence it is, that we ſhall the rather take unto our ſelves this boldnes, to beſeech you to add unto a liberal and beneficial, the care of a religious and pious
<pb facs="tcp:135400:3"/> education. We would not in any thing we have ſpoken, or ſhall hereafter ſpeak, intimate any ſuch reflexions on the deceaſed Parents, as to cauſe any to conceive they left their children altogether unprovided; They were not ſuch ſtrangers unto Scripture as not to know that <hi>children ought not to lay up for their Parents, but Parents for their children</hi> 
                     <note n="[d]" place="margin">2 Cor. 12. 14.</note>. God beſtowed a competent por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon them, which they ſo improv'd, as that they have provided that which is conſiderable for the ſubſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence and diſpoſal of thoſe that they have left behind them; Howſoever therefore we thankfully acknowledge any aſſiſtance in this kind alſo, yet the chief benefit will be to ſupply the parents abſence in their education. The feeding of children is one thing, and a leſſe thing; The breeding is another, and a greater; and the chief thing in breeding (which the godly Parents moſt deſired, and which we moſt humbly beg at your hands who are left and ſtand obliged to purſue their good affections and intendment) is, <hi>to bring them up in the nurture and admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition of the Lord</hi> 
                     <note n="[a]" place="margin">Epheſ. 6. 4.</note>, which endeavours ſhall be fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed (God aſſiſting) with our moſt earneſt prayers for their good ſucceſs.</p>
                  <p>The righteous God, <note n="[b]" place="margin">Heb. 6. 10.</note> remember, in much mercie, <note n="[c]" place="margin">Neh. 13. 22.</note> all your labours of love which you have ſhewed to his Name in miniſtring to his Saints, and abundantly recompence them in all ſpiritual and outward bleſſings on you and yours, which ſhall ſtill be the prayer of</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your much obliged ſervants in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> WILLIAM THOMAS <hi>Paſtor at</hi> Ubley. JOHN CHETWIND <hi>Paſtor at</hi> Wells.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:135400:4"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:135400:4"/>
                  <head>TO THE READER.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>GOOD READER,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Unerall diſcourſes are of <hi>antient uſe,</hi> and <hi>no leſs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit;</hi> the death of friends is an <hi>occaſional help,</hi> and needeth the moſt <hi>ſolemn way</hi> of improvement; that when affections are ſtirred up on an <hi>earthly occaſion,</hi> they may be converted <hi>to a ſpiritual uſe;</hi> the experience of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in this kinde is a ſufficient juſtification of the practice.</p>
                  <p>Beſides there is an <hi>whole vein</hi> of doctrine, concerning the <hi>frailty</hi> and <hi>mortality of man,</hi> the <hi>vanity of the creature,</hi> &amp;c. which runneth throughout the Scripture, &amp; would never be opened but upon theſe occaſions: certainly we that are to preach <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, 2 Tim. 4. 2. <hi>in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon,</hi> that is (as I ſuppoſe) in our <hi>ordinary courſe,</hi> and when God giveth <hi>ſpecial occaſion</hi> or <hi>a fair oportunity</hi> in his providence, may with ſafety enough to Conſcience improve <hi>funerall meetings</hi> to ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall edification and profit, there being uſually at ſuch meetings a great conflux of people, and their affections melted and ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the preſent Providence. 'Tis true we read nothing in Scripture of <hi>Funerall Rites</hi> by way <hi>of Precept,</hi> and the <hi>Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> bind not, all Nations are left to their <hi>Own Rites</hi> and <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes,</hi> provided they ſavour not of <hi>Idolatry</hi> or <hi>Superſtition;</hi> But yet the generall allowance of improving every occaſion, is warrant enough for <hi>a Sermon,</hi> and <hi>the Sermon</hi> a <hi>ſeaſonable comment</hi> upon the <hi>Providence;</hi> for every one cannot read without ſpectacles, and understand the diſpenſation of God <hi>without an interpreter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Beſides the Sermon, <hi>ſpeeches</hi> and <hi>commemorative Orations</hi> want not their uſe, when the parties deceaſed are perſons of known merit and uſefulnes; for 'tis not fit that their graces ſhould dye with them, and that vertue ſhould be defrauded of its publick honour, becauſe <hi>God</hi> 
                     <note n="(*)" place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. 30.</note> 
                     <hi>honoureth thoſe that honour him,</hi> the Church hath been always carefull to preſerve and enbalm their memory, and ſo is that promiſe made good, Prov. 10. 7. <hi>the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of the juſt ſhall be bleſſed, but the name of the wicked ſhall rot.</hi> The Lord would have the juſt remembred with praiſe and honorable mention, whereas the <hi>name</hi> of the wicked <hi>rotteth</hi> together with their <hi>carkas.</hi> If the <hi>worthy Authours</hi> of the enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sermon and exhortation had only deſigned in divulging their labours, to continue the memory and example of thoſe Saints and ſervants of God whoſe Funeralls gave an occaſion to theſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, I ſuppoſe nothing had been done unworthy a Chriſtian
<pb facs="tcp:135400:5"/> aim; prayſe and publick honour being <hi>a debt</hi> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e owe to the righteous, yea <note n="(*)" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Nazian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen</hi> funebri Orat. pro fratre Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſareo.</note> 
                     <hi>a debt (ſaith Nazianzen) that of all debts is moſt juſt:</hi> and as the Ancient Church was wont to preſerve the memory of the <hi>Saints</hi> in thoſe famous <note n="(*)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Sir Henry Spilman in verbo</hi> Dypticha.</note> 
                     <hi>Dyptichs,</hi> ſo might they ſeek to continue the memory of their graces in this <hi>publick record,</hi> that though <hi>being dead,</hi> they <hi>might yet ſpeak.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But they looked upon this as too <hi>private an aime</hi> for thy prof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, the matter here diſcuſſed is of a more publick and generall concernement, and exceedingly uſefull for theſe times, as 1. <hi>the laying to heart the death of Gods children,</hi> which hath ever been obſerved to be an intimation of approaching judgment, Iſa. 57. 1. When we ſee a ſhowre coming we make the more haſt to gather in the fruit, ſo Gods gathering in his Saints is a preſage of an <note n="[*]" place="margin">
                        <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 4.</note> enſuing ſtorme: and as the death of any <hi>private Saint</hi> is to be taken notice of, as being a conſiderable loſſe to the communities and ſocieties in which they are intereſted; ſo much more the death of <hi>Miniſters</hi> and thoſe that are called to publick office in the Church, becauſe of the eminency of their ſtation, and ſervice. I confeſſe the world thinketh not ſo, all that is called <hi>Miniſtry</hi> is now counted a <hi>burden,</hi> this is the great ſcorne and affront that we put upon Chriſt, his <hi>largeſs</hi> and <hi>Royal donative</hi> which he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on the Church in the <hi>day of his inauguration (when he aſcended up on high he gave Paſtors and teachers &amp;c.</hi> Eph. 4. 8, 9, 10, 11.) is reckoned as one of the grievances of the Nation, which by interpretation is as much as if we did bid Chriſt <hi>take his gift to himſelf, we care not for it;</hi> certainly if ever tis high time to make men ſenſible of the benefit of a Miniſtry, and the loſs of any that are qualified for ſo holy a work.</p>
                  <p>2. Another leſſon which (in ſuch tranſient reading as my preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing occaſions would allow) I have obſerved, <hi>is the ſurviving of the Word when Miniſters are gone,</hi> a Sermon dyeth not with the breath in which 'tis uttered, if it <hi>live</hi> not in <hi>our practice,</hi> it li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth in the <hi>records of Heaven,</hi> and <hi>in the effect of providence;</hi> as the <hi>words of the former Prophets,</hi> when they were dead and rotten in the grave. This with many other uſefull obſervations (for to name all were to foreſtall the work it ſelf) wilt thou meet with in theſe diſcourſes; which that they may be of great uſe and bleſſing to thy ſoule, as it is <hi>the aime</hi> of the reverend Authors, ſo it is the <hi>prayer</hi> of him who is,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Thine to ſerve thee in all Chriſtian offices,</hi> THOMAS MANTON.</signed>
                     <dateline>Newington, <date>May 16. 1653.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:135400:5"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>IMMANVEL,</hi> A SERMON Preached the twelfth day of AU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GUST. 1652.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>ZECH. 1. 5, 6.</bibl>
                     <q>
                        <p>Your Fathers where are they? and the Prophets, do they live for ever?</p>
                        <p>But my word, and my Statutes, which I comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded my ſervants the Prophets, did they not take hold of your Fathers?</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ad our conjoyned deſires and prayers prevailed, Our Deceaſed Friend, and your Reverend Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor, who in a ſilent Sermon from his Coffin Preacheth to us the Lecture of our Mortality, ſhould ſtil have been a living Voice, a burning and a ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Light.</p>
                  <p>But ſince our gracious God hath put a period to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:135400:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> his life and labours, and by his work hath mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted his will, as its our duty to ſubſcribe unto it, ſo it will be our wiſdom to improve it to our own <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 7. 2.</note> advantage; Following the Wiſemans Counſel, ſo to go into this Houſe of mourning, that by lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch providences to heart, we may be made better.</p>
                  <p>Its the deplorable extremity of humane corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to draw evil out of Gods good; abuſing thus his grace to wantoneſs, and his readineſs to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don to a Liberty of ſinning, as Spiders ſuck poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon from the ſweeteſt flowers.</p>
                  <p>Its the weakneſs of the fleſh, to apprehend that as evil, which God calls good.</p>
                  <p>Its the proper work and power of God, to bring good out of thoſe evils that are <hi>done by us.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Rhm. 8. 28.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>And its the excellency of Faith, to apprehend goodneſs in thoſe diſpenſations which our ſenſe tells us are evils <hi>done upon us.</hi> And this Faith doth, and Faith alone can do; becauſe it remains firm amongſt the violenteſt ſhakings, as gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning it ſelf, not according to the mutable, and variable inſtability of humane Occurrences, but according to the unchangeable foundations of Gods promiſes, like the Nodes of Compaſſes in the midſt of tempeſts, that are directed not by the Wind but Heavens.</p>
                  <p>The Bee (you know) hath an Innate quality, which other creatures want, to extract Hony out of (it may be) il-ſavouring Flowers; ſo gracious ſouls going into the Sanctuary, by the ſtrength of Faith, will be able to ſay, though other men can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, what the Pſalmiſt doth, Truly, God is good <note place="margin">Pſa. 73. 1.</note>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:135400:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Notwithſtanding, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now as God is good, and ſo to be acknowledged in all his dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, even in this ſad diſpenſation of his provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, whereby a deſerving Paſtor is removed from a deſiring People, and both the careful, and indulgents Parents within the compaſs of one week, from many tender and needing Orphans, ſo ought we to indeavour the improving of it to our own ſpiritual good. And therefore know, that Funeral ſolemnities are not for the ſolace of the dead (they are beyond our prayers or helps, though not reſpects) but for the comfort and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the living, who ought, as thoſe who came where <hi>Aſahel</hi> lay dead, to ſtand ſtill and <note place="margin">2 Sam. 2. 23.</note> conſider, what God expects they ſhould learn from the works of his hand, his deed having a voice to inſtruct us, as well as his word. To help you wherein, I ſhall crave your attentions to thoſe doctrinal truths, which from the word read, ſhall be commended and improved unto you. In the managing of which, as I vary from my uſual way of diſcourſe, my Apology is this; As in Feaſts, ſo in Sermons, we reſpect the Company, not our ſelves. <hi>Paul</hi> at <hi>Athens</hi> alters his ſtile.</p>
                  <p>The words are part of <hi>Zechariahs</hi> Penitential Sermon, compriſed in the ſix firſt verſes of this Propheſy, in which according to the reſolution of it by the Judicious <hi>Diodati)</hi> we have</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. The call to Repentance. <hi>v.</hi> 3. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, Turn unto me ſaith the Lord of Hoſts.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. Arguments to enforce this exhortation, and they are drawn from</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:135400:7"/>
                     <item>1. The good of ſo doing. <hi>v.</hi> 3. <hi>I will turn to you.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. The evil of not repenting
<list>
                           <item>1. Repreſented in the Hiſtory of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<list>
                                 <item>1. Sin. <hi>v.</hi> 4. <hi>They did not.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>2. Effects of ſin.
<list>
                                       <item>1. Gods wrath. <hi>v.</hi> 2. <hi>The Lord hath been ſore diſpleaſed,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                                       <item>2. Their puniſhment. <hi>v.</hi> 6. <hi>Did they not take hold,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>2. Hiſtory applyed. <hi>v.</hi> 4. <hi>Be not as your Fathers.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Now the words of my text, <hi>Your Fathers where are they,</hi> &amp;c. are inſerted for the amplification and inforcement of the exhortation, and by way of prevention to remove two forceable obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions that might weaken the ſtrength of thoſe Motives.</p>
                  <p>The hindrances are, what the Prophet foreſaw their corruptions would prompt them to ſay;
<list>
                        <item>1. You tel us of our Fathers; What is that to us? They are dead.</item>
                        <item>2. You tell us of the former Prophets; What is that to us? They are dead too.</item>
                     </list> to remove which, theſe words are by way of Conceſſion, as if God ſhould ſay, I grant you what you do object, your Fathers are dead, and the Prophets are dead, yet know, you have great reaſon to regard the preſent exhortations to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, that are now made to you by my Prophets,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:135400:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                     <hi>Haggai,</hi> and <hi>Zechariah,</hi> and others that are now ſent; Becauſe</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The examples of my Juſtice on your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers do ſtil live. <hi>Did it not take hold?</hi> yes it did, they have confeſſed it, and they <hi>returned and ſaid, like as the Lord of Hoſts thought to do unto us, according to our ways, and according to our doing, ſo hath he dealt with us.</hi> ver. 6.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The word which I commanded my Prophets, though the Prophets be dead, yet their words ſtil live. <hi>Did they not take hold?</hi> v. 6.</p>
                  <p>Thus have I given you that ſenſe and depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of the words, which I conceive moſt genu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine and proper, and ſhall not ſpend time needleſly in relating others judgements.</p>
                  <p>That being a good rule, for popular Preachers, which at my firſt entrance upon the work of the Miniſtry, I received from my ſometimes Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Friend Mr. <hi>Samuel Crook</hi> of famous memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, late Paſtor of <hi>Woragton,</hi> now with God. <hi>In vulgar auditories to pitch upon that ſenſe of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture which is moſt genuine, and not to diſtract hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers by mentioning various readings and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. That courſe rather ſavouring of oſtentation, than tending to inſtruction.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The words are plain and without difficulty; on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly take notice, that the Prophet by that queſtion, <hi>Where are they?</hi> Intends thus much; they are dead; according to that of <hi>Job, Man giveth up the Ghoſt, and where is he?</hi> and by that phraſe of <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken hold,</hi> or <hi>overtake,</hi> implies thus much, that Gods <note place="margin">Job 14. 10.</note> denounced judgements are as a proſecuting enemy,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:135400:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> that follows the purſute, and wil not ceaſe, til o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertaking they lay hold on, and hold faſt his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies.</p>
                  <p>Now in my paſſage to the main thing intended from the words read, give me leave to mention, and I ſhall but mention, the doctrines of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text, or at leaſt the moſt principal of them; which are theſe five that follow.</p>
                  <p>Turning men to God is the Preachers main <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>1</label> employment; The former Prophets, <hi>Zechariahs,</hi> St. <hi>Pauls,</hi> whom God ſent <hi>to open their eys and to</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Acts 26. 18, 20.</note> 
                     <hi>turn them from darkneſs to light, and from the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Satan unto God.</hi> This was, This is, Gods meſſengers imployment to perſwade ſuch, that have left Gods ways to follow their own, now to leave their own to follow Gods, to walk with their faces toward the Sun, that ſo they may have ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning light, and comfortable heat, when as turning their backs to the Sun, what ſee they but a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, the privation of light and heat? The bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing back of loſt Sheep to their Shepherd, of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digal children to their Father, the beſeeching ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to be reconciled, and by repentance to break off their ſins, is the proper work of Chriſts Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters.</p>
                  <p>Preſent enjoyments of ſignal mercies, yea great <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> deliverances, are no ground of future ſecurity, without renewed and renewing repentance. They were now but newly come forth of captivity, and ſo had received a mighty deliverance, yet ſhould they again break Gods Commandements, they know God would have been angry with them <note place="margin">Ezra 9. 13, 14.</note> til he had conſumed them, ſo that there ſhould be
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:135400:8"/> The doctrine of Repentance is always neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>3</label> to be preached, but eſpecially, then when mercies are enjoyed, and we are in a proſperous eſtate, In which the Heart is exceeding apt to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get God. <hi>Latet anguis in Herba,</hi> A deadly poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is many times ſecretly conveyed under a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant reliſh: for as when men are moſt hot, they are then moſt ſubject to take dangerous colds; ſo when Chriſtians enjoy all things outwardly well, (as <hi>David,</hi> when at peace) then are they in great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt danger of ſpiritual miſcarriages. The doctrine then of Repentance is always needful, it was the firſt doctrine preached by Chriſt, The diſciples, <hi>John,</hi> fit for every Auditory, for all times.</p>
                  <p>Other diſcourſes may be profitable, but this is neceſſary.</p>
                  <p>An impenitent obſtinacy againſt, and under the <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>4</label> means of grace, is an aggravated impiety.</p>
                  <p>Forefathers examples are no plea for impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency, <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>5</label> no privilege for impunity, and yet (as the Jewes) we are exceeding apt to plead them, when <note place="margin">Jer. 44. 17</note> they are ſo far from countenancing that they ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravate offences.</p>
                  <p>Having thus mentioned the doctrines of the context, I now come to Conſider the truths of the words Read, and they are two, the firſt I ſhall but touch, and the ſecond Inſiſt on as more ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to the preſent occaſion.</p>
                  <p>Your fathers are dead, yet they were took Hold <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Text. </seg>
                     </label> on, and they confeſt it. Whence;</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Examples of God juſtice on foregoing people are</hi> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <hi>left recorded, and ought to be improved, as warnings to following generations.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:135400:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p> As what was forewritten, ſo what was foredone, was for our learning; and thus the Apoſtle tels us <note place="margin">Rom. 15. 4.</note> that the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were overthrown in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and theſe things were <hi>our examples to the</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10. 5, 6.</note> 
                     <hi>intent, we ſhould not luſt after evil things as they alſo luſted.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hence God calls us to <hi>Remember the dayes of</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Deut. 32. 7.</note> 
                     <hi>old, and to conſider the years of many generations;</hi> and Chriſt wils his diſciples to recall to mind what <note place="margin">Luke 17. 32.</note> was done long before, even to <hi>Remember Lots wife,</hi> who was turned into a Pillar of Salt, a viſible and laſting Monument; whereas God might have blown her up as Salt-Peter, or ſunk her down as Coral, he fixeth her as a Pillar, and calls to us to remember it, that we may fetch thence where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall to ſeaſon our unſavory lives. Thus Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotes are made of poyſon, and Treacle from Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers.</p>
                  <p>The ground of which truth is, becauſe God is alwaies the ſame. His paſt dealings are the diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of his future; they who are alike in fault muſt expect to be alike in ſuffering. If <hi>Iſraels</hi> Princes <note place="margin">Iſa. 1. 9. 10.</note> commit the ſins of <hi>Sodom,</hi> as they ſhall have their names, ſo, without repentance, ſhall they have their ſorrows.</p>
                  <p>Learn then hence how to improve Hiſtories recorded, not read them to ſatisfie curioſitie, but to inſtruct and caution thee. Not as thoſe who are well, that hear, or read the rules of Phyſicians, but as ſick perſons, that attend ſuch diſcourſes that they may make uſe of, and apply the receipts preſcribed.</p>
                  <p>Let us thus go to <hi>Shiloh,</hi> and conſider what God did <note place="margin">Jer. 7. 12.</note>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:135400:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> dit to it for the wickedneſs of his people. Let us of <hi>England</hi> remember the ſeven Churches of <hi>Aſia,</hi> the Nation of the Jews, who were as <hi>Gideon</hi>'s <note place="margin">Judg. 6. 37, 38.</note> fleece, firſt wet with Heavenly dew, when all the reſt of the world was dry, and now dry, when great part of the world beſides is wet; for look, <note place="margin">Exod. 10. 21, 23.</note> as it was in <hi>Egypt,</hi> the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> had light when all the reſt were dark; but at Chriſts death <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Luke 25. 45.</note> was in darkneſs, when all the reſt was light: ſo had the Jews at firſt Gods oracles, and ſo, Chriſts proffers, when the Gentiles were ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers; but now the Gentiles are ingrafted, and the Jews cut off: ſo may it be with us of <hi>England,</hi> who have long enjoyed the Sun-ſhine of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, when other Nations and people have been without it, we may be for our unworthineſs caſt off, and others received; therefore let us ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member former examples, that we may ſtil apply them to our ſelves, and know what Chriſt is wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling we ſhould mind, that <hi>except we repent, we ſhall</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Luke 13. 3, 5.</note> 
                     <hi>all likewiſe periſh.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Having thus given you a brief account of the firſt truth of the text, I now come to the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the main Doctrine, and that which is moſt pertinent to the occaſion of our preſent meeting, and that grounded on theſe words,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Prophets, do they live for ever? But my words</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Text.</note> 
                     <hi>and my Statutes, which I commanded my ſervants the Prophets, did they not take hold of your Fathers?</hi> Whence obſerve,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Though Preachers dye, yet Sermons live.</hi> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                     </label>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>All fleſh is graſs, but the word of the Lord endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1. 24, 25.</note> 
                     <hi>for ever.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:135400:10"/>
                  <p> Though Chriſts Embaſſadors are mortal men; yet their Embaſſage is an immortal errand, which will have its effect even after the death of the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger. Miniſters are earthen pitchers, that may, and muſt diſſolve into duſt; But the Goſpel which they bring is water drawn from an everlaſting <note place="margin">Iſa. 12. 3. Rev. 14. 6.</note> Well, and of an everlaſting nature, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues when the pitcher is broke. When the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels were returned to Heaven, the Shepherds re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred <note place="margin">Luke 2. 15.</note> their words.</p>
                  <p>For the firſt part of this Doctrine, That Preachers dye, you have a viſible proof this day before you, and no wonder: For its appointed for all men, (and Miniſters are but men) once to dye.</p>
                  <p>For the ſecond part of this Doctrine, that Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons live, it is, though not ſo viſibly, yet as ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly evidenced in the words of the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah. For as the rain cometh down, and the Snow from</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Iſa. 55. 10, 11.</note> 
                     <hi>Heaven, and returneth not thither, but watereth the earth, and maketh it bring forth and bud, that it may give ſeed to the ſower, and bread to the eater; ſo ſhall my word be that goeth forth out of my mouth, it ſhall not return unto me void but it ſhall accompliſh that which I pleaſe, and it ſhall proſper in the thing whereunto I ſent it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And therefore, though at preſent obſtinate ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners regard not Gods meſſages or meſſengers, yet whether they wil hear, or whether they wil forbear, they ſhall one day <hi>know, that there hath</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Eze. 2. 4, 5</note> 
                     <hi>been a Prophet amongſt them.</hi> The word Preachd by Gods faithful Miniſters is an immortal and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptible <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1. 23</note> ſeed, that wil moſt aſſuredly bring forth ſome fruit, either for our good or evil.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:135400:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> 1. For good; ſo this good Seed produceth in us the eternal being of immortal grace. Now as <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1. 23.</note> natural Parents may dye, yet leave their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren living, much more ſpiritual Parents, who <note place="margin">1 Cor. 4. 15.</note> beget Converts through the word of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel; who if they leave not ſpiritual children here below, yet wil certainly find them in Heaven; Grace once given being a Free-hold of inheritance that cannot be forfeited; For <hi>he that is born of God hath the ſeed of God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1 Joh. 3. 9.</note> 
                     <hi>in him, and cannot ſin;</hi> and ſo by conſequence cannot finally miſcarry, God having in his Covenant ingaged, as never to <note place="margin">Heb. 13. 5.</note> leave us, ſo to write his Laws in our hearts, and put his fear before our eyes, that we ſhall <note place="margin">Ier. 32. 40.</note> never leave him.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. For evil. Thus the text, <hi>Did not my words take hold?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hence Chriſt tells us, that the word which he had Preached to the Jews ſhould judge them <note place="margin">Iohn. 12. 48. Mat. 16. 19.</note> at the laſt day, and that what his Apoſtles did bind on earth ſhould be bound in Heaven.</p>
                  <p>Thus the Doctrine lieth evident before you, and you are, I queſtion not, fully convinced of the truth of this aſſertion, That Preachers dying, leave Sermons living and laſting, and which wil <note place="margin">2 Cor. 2. 16.</note> have their effect, either of good, as a ſavour of life to life, or of evil, as a ſavour of death to death. Not that all which pious Preachers ſpeak in Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons ſhall laſt ſo long; No, There may be much <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3. 12.</note> Wood, Hay, Stubble, built on the foundation, which wil not endure the fire, but the foundation
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:135400:11"/> rightly layed ſhall alwaies laſt; the proffers and tenders of Chriſts to Sinners ſhall have their ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, either in their converſion, or to their grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter condemnation. Thus then, It is not the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom <note place="margin">Joh. 3. 19. 1 Cor. 1. 17.</note> of words, but the Word of wiſdom that abides for ever.</p>
                  <p>Having thus diſpatched the doctrinal part of this truth, it remains that I improve it to you by application.</p>
                  <p>In the managing of which, I ſhall joyn both the truth of the text, and the providence of this time, the ſad occaſion of our preſent meeting, and ſhall endeavour to make uſe of both, by acquainting you what they ſpeak.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. To this Congregation, to whom this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed Preacher was a faithful Paſtor.</item>
                     <item>2. To us in the Miniſtry, the ſurviving diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſers of Goſpel myſteries.</item>
                     <item>3. To all in general.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Firſt, you that are related as a particular flock of Chriſt to him that's gone, and to him that ſpeaks, Know, that this word, this work, ſpeaks much to you. I ſhall divide my diſcourſe into a twofold Chanel.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Reſpecting him that is gone.</item>
                     <item>2. Reſpecting the opportunities of grace that do or may remain amongſt you.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Firſt then know, that this truth, that <hi>Preachers dye, but Gods word never dieth,</hi> and the death of this our Reverend Brother, hath much to ſay to us. I ſhall give it in ſix particulars, and I deſire you would ſeriouſly lay them to heart, as they proceed
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:135400:11"/> from a mind that doth ſeriouſly and earneſtly deſire your good in what is ſpoken.</p>
                  <p>Firſt own Gods goodneſs in enjoying of him ſo <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> long: for though ſad providence hath more ſuddain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly than was expected taken him from us, yet may we not be unmindfull of Gods goodneſs in lending him ſo long, as a great mercy to this place and people, for whom (as <hi>Paul)</hi> he ſpent himſelf in the painfull exerciſe of his Miniſterial gifts. He was a burning and a ſhining light, who did not waſt out, but wear out; who did not ſmother out, but burn'd, yea flam'd out, who ſpent his Spirits that he might inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally communicate Gods Spirit, and inliven yours, and they that know the paſſages of his ſickneſs are very confident, that it was not the violence of the Wind that blew forth his Lamp, but the Oyl was ſpent, and the flame muſt ceaſe. Let us then remember and own him for a mercy, who was ſo ſucceſſively pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and uſefull in his generation.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, we have reaſon all of us, but eſpecially <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> he that ſpeaks, and you (late his charge) that are ſpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken to, and all others that hear me this day, to lament our loſs. I may juſtly take up <hi>Eliſha</hi>'s Lamentation, when he ſaw <hi>Elijah</hi> gone to Heaven before him. <hi>Ah</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">2 Kings 21. 12.</note> 
                     <hi>my Father, my Father, the chariot of</hi> Iſrael <hi>and the horſemen thereof;</hi> and you have reaſon to ſay, Alas my Brother. <hi>Alas our Paſtor.</hi> God expects that we ſhould value our loſs, and expreſs it by our lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for it. And the moſt of us, if not all have cauſe to repent of our ſin, who have ſlighted the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy lent us; Who have ſlept in our day, and not wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked anſwerably to this light. When Children wax wanton, and throw wholeſome food to the Dogs, its
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:135400:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> time to remove the Tables; if <hi>Epheſus</hi> wil not repent, <note place="margin">Rev. 2. 5.</note> and do her firſt works, Chriſt threatens to come quickly and remove her Candleſtick. And whether our unthankfulneſs, and unfruitfulneſs, have not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked the Lord to deprive us of this his ſervants Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, I am afraid to deny, though I cannot deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine. Let us (however) lament our loſs, repent of our ſin.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, are there any amongſt us (I could wiſh <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> there were none, but I fear there are too many) to be found, the more ſad their condition, that have not profited as they ſhould have done by the labours of this ſervant of God? Let ſuch lay the blame where its due; at their own doors. Conſider the Parable of the Sower, That tells us, There were <note place="margin">Mat. 13.</note> four grounds on which Seed was caſt, and but one fruitful. Where was the fault? Was it in the Seed, or Sower? No, they were the ſame, but the faults lay in the grounds themſelves. So is it with the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of the word, when a very few receive advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, and the greateſt number remain unfruitful. Say not thou then, the Phyſick was weak, but thy di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper was ſtrong. Say not the meat was unwhole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but know thy Stomach was foul. Now its a true Rule in Phyſick, <hi>Corrupta corpora quo magis nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris, eo magis laedis,</hi> Impure Bodies, the more you nouriſh the more you harm. They who have bad eyes think the sky alwaies cloudy. The fault may be, and moſt times is, in our ſelves, when we are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to lay it upon others. People may be unprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble under the moſt powerful Miniſtry, becauſe of their own dulneſs and negligence. Do not then in this caſe, as that man, who complained of the rough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:135400:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> of the way, when he had a thorn in his foot, or that Woman <hi>Plutarch</hi> mentions, who being ſuddain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtruck blind, bid them open the Windows.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, Remember, I beſeech you, the Doctrine <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> of the text, That though your Preacher be dead, yet his Sermons live, and wil live for ever. You ſhall know that he hath been a Prophet of the Lord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you. It was the deſire of his Soul on his ſick Bed, that this Congregation would conſider his death, and lay it to heart; That they who have not profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by his Sermons in his life, might now profit by his departure. For aſſure your ſelves, Gods word, by whomſoever ſpoken (as the Sword of <hi>Saul)</hi> wil <note place="margin">2 Sam. 1. 22.</note> never return empty, any more than the rain doth, as that place formerly cited out of the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> fully ſhews. So ſhall not the word of God ſpoken by any that are faithfull return empty, but proſper in the thing whereto God ſends it.</p>
                  <p>Bleſſed be God, that ſome of you know that Gods word by him hath taken hold of you for good. He hath not wanted the Seals of his Apoſtleſhip. And <note place="margin">1 Cor. 9. 2.</note> (what ever vain men ſay to the contrary) converſion of Souls to God by the Miniſtry is an Apoſtolical ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of the rightfulneſs and lawfulneſs of the Miniſterial call, and ſuch a Seal, yea divers ſuch Seals had our deceaſed friend. Some that were in Heaven before him, and others that are ſtil below, did and do acknowledge him their ſpiritual Father. And Friends, you of this City and Congregation ſhall know that his words wil take hold, if not to ſave you, which was his aim and deſire, yet to judge you at the laſt day, which is your fault, and wil be your mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery; for God wil certainly <hi>puniſh as the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Hoſ. 7. 12.</note>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:135400:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                     <hi>hath heard.</hi> That the Goſpel by him, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Preach'd prevails for good, is Gods grace, that it proves a ſavour of death to death, is our ſin.</p>
                  <p>Now never wonder that ſuch diametrical oppoſite effects proceed from the ſame cauſe. You wil not, if you conſider the reaſon to be, not in the Cauſe, but in the Subject; not in the word, but in the hearts of thoſe who hear it. Chriſt who came to be the light of the world, came alſo for judgement into this <note place="margin">Joh. 9. 39.</note> world, that they which ſee not might ſee, and that they which ſee might be made blind. Chriſt who is a Corner ſtone to ſome, yet becomes a Rock of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſe <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 6, 7, 8.</note> to others; that meat which ſtrengthens healthy bodies, yet breeds diſeaſes in corrupted Stomachs; and its obſerv'd by Naturaliſts, That the ſmel of a ſweet Ointment comforteth the Dove, but killeth the Hornet; The ſame heat which ſoftneth Wax, hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth Clay; That Flower which yields Hony to the Bee, yields poyſon to the Spider; That fire which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines Gold, conſumes the droſs: So that Goſpel by the mouths of Gods Servants, and by the mouth of this his ſervant, which hath been inſtrumental to ſave ſome, wil moſt aſſuredly at the laſt day condemn others. For this indeed is the judgement heightning ſin, that <hi>light is come into the world, and men love dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs rather than light.</hi> And accordingly it wil be more <note place="margin">Joh. 3. 19.</note> tolerable for <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorroh,</hi> for <hi>Tunnis</hi> and <hi>Algier,</hi> at the day of judgement, than for this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, for this Congregation, if the word of Gods grace be not ſavingly entertained. <hi>Woe unto thee</hi> Chora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zin, <hi>woe unto thee</hi> Bethſaida, ſaith our Saviour, <hi>for if the mighty works which were done in you, had been</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 11. 21, 22.</note> 
                     <hi>done in</hi> Tyre <hi>and</hi> Sidon, <hi>they had repented long agoe in Sackcloth and aſhes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:135400:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p> Fiftly, Continue in, and hold faſt, and ſtill cleave <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> to thoſe inſtructions which your late Paſtor in the diſcharge of his Miniſterial employment hath deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to you. His ſoul was, and my ſoul is, your Pledge that they are the truths of Jeſus. We dare not be as ſome; <hi>who make merchandiſe of you with</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>feigned words.</hi> We tremble to be as many, who <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt the word of God, but as of ſincerity, but as of God,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">2 Cor. 2. 17.</note> 
                     <hi>in the ſight of God ſpeak we in Chriſt.</hi> And therefore follow that Counſel given by <hi>Paul, As you have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Col. 2. 6, 7.</note> 
                     <hi>Chriſt Jeſus the Lord, ſo walk ye in him, rooted and built up in him, and eſtabliſhed in the Faith as yee have been taught.</hi> Be rooted, be fixed, be not as Reeds ſhaken with every Wind, (as Children) toſſed to <note place="margin">Eph. 4. 14.</note> and fro, and carried about with every doctrine; No, but as Trees of righteouſneſs, which ſtand faſt in the place where God hath planted them. Be ye (as men) ſetled, and grounded in the truth. O how change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and child-like are many wanton hearers, whom you may win with an apple, and loſe with a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? Be not <hi>ambulantes in Conſilio,</hi> ſcatterers of your <note place="margin">Jer. 3. 13.</note> wayes; who ſo take a taſte of all courſes, muſt needs do evil; who ſo give themſelves a liberty to run af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all pretended Teachers, muſt needs learn evil. Therefore good was that Counſel to the Hebrews, <hi>Be not carried about with divers and ſtrange doctrines,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 13. 9.</note> 
                     <hi>for its a good thing that the heart be eſtabliſhed with grace.</hi> Intimating thus much, that <hi>unſetled hearers have uneſtabliſhed hearts.</hi> And worth our obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is that character of falſe doctrines given in the original word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, We render it, various, divers; It ſignifieth properly, <hi>Varii Coloris, Parti-coloured doctrines,</hi> of ſeveral threads; which have no agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment one with another.</p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:135400:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p> And certainly were there nothing elſe, yet this were enough to convince the doctrines of many to be falſe, eſpecially of ſuch who caſting dirt in the faces of Chriſts publike Miniſters, arrogate the name of his Meſſengers to themſelves, and <hi>ſay they are A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Rev. 2. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>when they are not;</hi> Namely their inconſiſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, variableneſs, and diſagrement. And this may ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently commend unto you the doctrines taught you by your deceaſed Paſtor, by him that now ſpeaks, and all other faithful Miniſters, which have occaſionally by their procurement ſpoken to you in the name of the Lord, <hi>viz.</hi> That there is no inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feering, no croſſing, but a ſweet Harmony and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. Truth is in all his parts alike, and ſuch who are acted by the Spirit of truth, in thoſe points which are materially and fundamentally neceſſary, (howſoever <note place="margin">Phil. 3 16.</note> they may differ in ſome circumſtantials) <hi>ſpeak the ſame things;</hi> Whereas falſe teachers, not only dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer one from another, but alſo from themſelves, ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom keeping themſelves in the ſame ſtation either of place or doctrine, but are, as <hi>Jude</hi> calls them, <hi>wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring Stars,</hi> that ſettle no where, but are alwaies in <note place="margin">Jude. 13.</note> uncertain motions. Solid Chriſtians are fixed Stars, counterfeit profeſſors are wandring Planets, now Planets, as Aſtrologers ſpeak, according to their Conjunction vary their Influence; ſo is it with unſtay'd profeſſors, they are according to their conjunction, Let one man Preach this thing, they are of his mind, if another new-af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected Teacher Preach the contrary, they cloſe with that. But I hope better things of you, for whom it was the prayer of your late Paſtor, it is and ſhall be
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:135400:14"/> the prayer of him that now ſpeaks to you, what was St. <hi>Peters,</hi> 1 <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. c. 10. v. <hi>That the God of all grace would make you perfect, ſtabliſh, ſtrengthen, ſettle you. Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sixtly, Know beloved, you of this place, that God <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> expects from you a walking anſwerable unto the care pains and labour that he hath exerciſed towards you. Where God gives much, he expects much, <note place="margin">Luke 12. 48.</note> and certainly you have had much perſwaſion unto Chriſt, exhortation unto duty, conviction of ſin, precept upon precept, line upon line, here a little and <note place="margin">Iſa 28. 10.</note> there a little, as <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old had. Now what is Gods expectation, but that you ſhould not ſhame your keeping, nor diſhonour your keeper, but that you would manifeſt that you have been taught of God, and make your profiting to appear by your practiſe of, and continuance in, that which is good? That you would not be as <hi>Pharaohs</hi> lean kine ſtil ill <note place="margin">Gen 41. 22.</note> favoured after they had devoured the fat ones. That you ſhould not be like other men, as others who have not had the ſame means of grace. Content not your ſelves with knowledge, or deſires after it, but look that your practiſe be anſwerable to your knowledge. Knowledge is neceſſary, but its not ſufficient; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is not to be deſired for it ſelf only, but for practiſe, which is indeed the life of knowledge, and renders it a bleſſing. For ſinful ſouls are as corrupt bodies, who have often great appetites, but ſmall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion. Now meat not diſgeſted, encumbers and breeds diſquieting diſeaſes; ſo knowledge not put in practiſe perverts the ſoul, and makes the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of it, Satans more ſerviceable inſtruments. Let us then follow Chriſt in ſincere obedience to plain
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:135400:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> truths, rather than trouble our ſelves with curious knotty and difficult matters, that at beſt do but fil our brains with notions, and uſually our hearts with pride, and rarely, if ever advance, Gods glory by us, or his grace in us.</p>
                  <p>Its the practiſe of good, and continuance in it, that God expects, <hi>as you have received Chriſt Jeſus, the</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Col. 2. 6.</note> 
                     <hi>Lord, ſo walk in him, and that to the end.</hi> A Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an hath ſtil his <hi>plus ultra,</hi> More to do. He that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueth to the end ſhall be ſaved; perſeverance to the end, brings a Crown without end.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Aarons</hi> Garments were <hi>Talares,</hi> down to the feet. And the Law forbad Tayl-leſs creatures to be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd in Sacrifice. Let it be your care then not only to lay aſide your ſins for a time, as the Serpent his poyſon, till he hath drank, but reſolve to part with them for ever, do with them as <hi>Jacob</hi> did with his Idols, bury them under the Oak, and ſay as <hi>Ephraim</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Gen. 35. 4.</note> of his Idols, <hi>What have I to do any more with them?</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Hoſ. 14. 8.</note> 
                     <hi>Let your light ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſee your good works, and glorifie your heavenly Father,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 5. 16.</note> and thereby let it appear that you have been with Jeſus, and Chriſt hath been with you. Theſe are the truths which your dead Paſtor by my mouth ſpeaks to you, and be ye prevailed withall, To own Gods goodneſs in your enjoying of him ſo long, to lament your loſs, to blame your ſelves, if you have not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited by his labours as you ought; to remember, that Gods word never dyes, though Miniſters do; to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in what you have heard, and to walk anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably to the truths you have been taught both by your late Paſtor now dead, and by your ſurviving teacher that now ſpeaks unto you. Wee dare not
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:135400:15"/> bring to you that which is not cleer to us to be the mind of God. I am confident of it, that nothing in the courſe of his Miniſtry was delivered by my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Fellow-labourer now deceaſed, but what he was aſſured of the truth of in his own conſcience. He did not preſs any thing upon you, which God had not firſt ſetled on his own heart, that it was the truth of Chriſt. And let this ſuffice to be ſpoken to this Congregation, reſpecting their Paſtor deceaſed.</p>
                  <p>I now ſhall addreſs my ſelf unto you in reſpect of the opportunities of grace that do, or may remain a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you. And that ſhall be in this general exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
                  <p>Return to God by them; Lay hold upon them; Be careful to improve them; Make a good uſe of them. <hi>Your Fathers are dead, and the Prophets do they live for ever? But my word and my Statutes, which I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded my ſervants the Prophets, did they not take hold of your Fathers?</hi> ſaith the Text. This Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet is dead, and he that ſpeaks ſhall dye, But their words ſhall live for ever.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>While you have the light therefore walk in it.</hi> Its <note place="margin">John 12. 35.</note> your opportunity, improve it. <hi>He that gathereth in Summer, is a wiſe Son: but he that ſleepeth in Harveſt,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Prov. 10. 5.</note> 
                     <hi>is a Son that cauſeth ſhame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Two things there are which render men truly wiſe, Firſt the knowledge of what is to be done, and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly the knowledge of the time when its to be done. <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, <hi>There is a time for all things.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Eccl. 3.</note> And that every thing is beautiful done in its due ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. It was a ſpeech of <hi>Antigonus,</hi> being provoked to fight by <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> upon a diſadvantage, <hi>Mea mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia non magis armorum eſt quam temporum?</hi> My war
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:135400:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> is managed by Times as well as by Arms. Accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it his beſt military prudence, to take his oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of time, as well as to provide good Souldiers. Idlers in their youth, prove commonly beggars in their age.</p>
                  <p>They that Sing in Summer ſhall mourn and weep <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Aeſtate Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cineris Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me jejuna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris. Fronte ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pillata eſt,</hi> &amp;c. Heb. 3. 7, 8. Iſa. 55. 6. John 12. 35.</note> in Winter.</p>
                  <p>Thoſe five fooliſh Virgins witneſs this, who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>providedly ſlept when the Bridegroom came, and therefore were ſhut out from the Wedding. Hence thoſe exhortations, of <hi>Not hardning our hearts to day, while it is called to day; of ſeeking God while he may be found; of walking in the light while we have it.</hi> Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove then preſent opportunities by an immediate returning unto God. Put not off repentance till here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. Think not that the practiſe of Repentance, as that Popiſh Prelate ſaid of the doctrine of <hi>Juſtification by Faith only, that 'tis a good Supper Doctrine.</hi> No, but know that God calls thee to <hi>Remember him thy Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Eccl. 12. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>in the dayes of thy youth.</hi> Its true indeed, that, <hi>Nunquam ſera eſt ad bonos mores via.</hi> True repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance is never too late. But yet in this caſe</p>
                  <q>Sera nimis vita eſt craſtina, vive Hodie.</q>
                  <p>A reſolved late repentance is uſually prevented by an intervening death.</p>
                  <p>We have a day of Mercy, if we neglect that, God hath a day of Juſtice, and he will not neglect that. Then Jeſus Chriſt the now deſpiſed Lamb will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear as an unreſiſtable Lion. Then they who now <note place="margin">Pr. 1. L.</note> ſtop their ears at Gods call, will find Gods ſtopt at theirs, and therefore, To day while it is called to day, Harden not your Hearts. Time paſt is gone, Time to <note place="margin">Aeſtas non ſemper fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erit, compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite nidos.</note> come may find us gone. Provide then eternal hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:135400:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> manſions, before theſe earthly tabernacles are diſſolved.</p>
                  <p>That I may perſwade you to this care, I ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force it on you by theſe two arguments.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Our eternal welfare depends on it. As men ſow, ſo they reap, as the tree falls, ſo it lies. <hi>Non relinquitur Hoſtia pro peccatis mortuo in peccatis, nec deſcendit in inferos ſanguis effuſus ſuper terram.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It was a Poetical fiction, that what every man af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected in this life, with that he ſhould be ſolaced in the Eliſyan Fields. The moral is a certain truth. That look, what men are in this world, that ſhall they be hereafter; they ſhall not hereafter be numbred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Sons of <hi>Sion,</hi> who were here the ſlaves of Satan. For know, that ſpiritual Eunuches that bring forth no good works, Baſtards that are not the ſeed of God, the Inceſtuous brood of <hi>Ammonites</hi> and <hi>Moabites</hi> that are born of worldly luſts, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcences, ſhall be more certainly excluded the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of the Saints in Heaven, than were the Corporal from the Congregation of <hi>Iſrael</hi> upon earth. Let us then provide our ſelves a remedy whilſt <note place="margin">Deut. 23. 3</note> there is time, and gain an intereſt in Chriſts righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs before we come to judgement, that ſo Chriſts tribunal may be to us as Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> not as Mount <hi>Sinai.</hi> That we having delighted our ſelves here in the Law of the Lord, may ſtand in the Congregation <note place="margin">Pſal. 1. 11</note> of the righteous, when others fly and fall. Delay not the doing of that which muſt be once done, or <note place="margin">Cum mora non tuta eſt, totis incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere remis Utile—Cras, Cras, &amp; ſic nihil ſit.</note> elſe thou art for ever undone. You ſee there is dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in delay; and its a good rule, <hi>A ſpeedy endeavour is exceeding neceſſary where delay is full of danger.</hi> Let us not ſay as too many do, To morrow we will do, and ſo its not done at all.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:135400:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> 2. Opportunities of grace are uncertain. The door may be ſhut, the light may be removed from us, or we may be removed from it; and therefore good is that Counſel of <hi>Solomon, All that thine hand ſhall</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Eccl. 9. 10.</note> 
                     <hi>find to do, do it with all thy power, for there is neither work, nor invention, nor knowledge, nor wiſdom in the grave whither thou goeſt. Lay up then in ſtore a good foundation againſt the time to come, that when thou</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6. 19.</note> 
                     <hi>leaveſt all other holds, thou mayſt lay hold on eternal life.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The time of the Goſpel is but a day, the time of our life is but a moment, whilſt thou haſt then the price in thine hand, get wiſdom, and ſtand not as thoſe therefore rebuked in the parable, all the day idle; I <note place="margin">Mat. 20. 7.</note> am ſure, you cannot ſay, no man hath hired you.</p>
                  <p>We ſhould count that Priſoner exceeding fooliſh, that would refuſe a pardon profered, and not look after it till the judge comes. And that traveller un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, that having far to go will not ſet forth till the Sun be ſet. The Stork knoweth his time, and ſhall <note place="margin">Jer. 8. 7. Gen. 27.</note> not we? <hi>Jacob</hi> was but newly gone with the bleſſing, yet <hi>Eſau</hi> came to late. They who neglected gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Manna in the ſix dayes, in vain expected it the ſeventh. They who refuſe the profers of grace in <note place="margin">Exod. 16. 27.</note> this life, may hereafter ſeek for entrance, but ſhall not be admitted. Improve then your time, your <note place="margin">Mat. 7. 1.</note> means, your preſent opportunities.</p>
                  <p>I hope you are ready to ask this queſtion, What ſhall we do?</p>
                  <p>In anſwering this queſtion my purpoſe is to ſhew you ſomewhat largely what God expects from you, that you may improve preſent opportunities of grace.</p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:135400:17"/>
                  <p> Firſt, Hear from God as often as thou mayeſt by the voice of his ſervants, the faithful appointed Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards and diſpenſers of Goſpel myſteries. I have been large upon this ſubject lately, yet give me leave now again to mind you, that its the great deſign that Satan now drives, the great ſin, the great miſery of this Land, to endeavour to overthrow the power, and vigour, and force of the Preaching of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel by the Miniſtry of men.</p>
                  <p>What the iniquity of former times could not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs by ſtopping the mouths of ſuch Preachers as were good, that the ſubtilty of Satan hath indeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in our dayes, and hath too much prevailed in that indeavour, by opening the mouths of ſuch as are bad, Who to cry up themſelves, not only cry down o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but even the Ordinances of Chriſt themſelves. And herein the Lord open our eyes, and the eyes of all this Land, and thine Chriſtian Reader, to ſee and conſider this Stratagem of Satan, who makes ſome, by ſeeming to cry up the purity, overthrow the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Preaching. For I pray you obſerve.</p>
                  <p>Satan doth not directly cry down all Preaching, he will not tell you (though he intend that in the end) that you muſt not hear at all. No: He knows full well that natural conſcience (not ſeared) wil imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly deny that perſuaſion. Such down-right dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling would be the way to diſcover himſelf, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore transforming himſelf into an Angel of Light, he beſets in another method, blaſting the publike <note place="margin">2 Cor, 14. 14, 15.</note> Miniſtry of Jeſus Chriſt with odious names, if not as Anti-Chriſtian (the uſuall term of ſuch who ſpeak againſt thoſe who cannot ſpeak for themſelves) yet as leſs pure than others of another way, and ſo ſhut up the Kingdom of Heaven (which
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:135400:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> according to Chriſts promiſe hath been given to our <note place="margin">Mat. 21. 43.</note> Nation, and hath (bleſſed be Gods holy name) both in former and later days brought forth its fruit with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the narrow compaſs of ſuch and ſuch ſocieties.</p>
                  <p>And thus Satan by force dividing between <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Apollos,</hi> and <hi>Cephas,</hi> inſtilling that miſchievous <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 12.</note> poyſon, of <hi>having the truth of Chriſt with reſpect of perſons,</hi> and ſo by pretending to purer, doth at laſt <note place="margin">James 2. 1.</note> (which is his main drift) cauſe man to fall off from a conſciencious reſpect unto any of Gods Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. I appeal unto thee good Reader, and am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident thine experience doth witneſs the truth of this diſcovery. Do not we daily ſee, that thoſe who throw away their wonted reſpects to Chriſts ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Miniſtry, give themſelves a liberty firſt to hear any, and then afterward to hear none? <hi>Ahab</hi> that could not away with one true Prophet that counſeld him for his good, yet hears and follows four hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred falſe ones, to his own ruin. Attend then I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech <note place="margin">1 Kings. 22. 22.</note> you with care and conſcience unto Gods <hi>ſent Meſſengers,</hi> by whoſe preaching it pleaſeth him to ſave <note place="margin">Rom. 10. 15.</note> ſuch as beleeve. Hear from him by them as often as you may, and if you ſay, Can any good come that way? I anſwer, Come and ſee. Look not on the meaneſs of the inſtruments, but who works by them, as Chriſt bid the Herodians on the penny, whoſe i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage it bore. For if God be the worker, he is able <note place="margin">Luke 20. 24.</note> by the ſmalleſt means to bring to paſs the greateſt ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects. The ſound of Rams-Horns commiſſionated <note place="margin">Judges 6.</note> by him, blows down the walls of <hi>Jericho;</hi> The ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering Sand keeps in the billows of the Sea, which Braſen walls could not: So God being the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, the fooliſhneſs of Preaching converts and ſaves. <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>1.</note>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:135400:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> Neglect not then the ſpiritual opportunities that are put into your hands. Suffer not every ſlight and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vial occaſion to keep you from them. God tells us, that when and where a famine of the word is, people ſhall <hi>run from one end of the Land to another, and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Amo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 11.</note> 
                     <hi>from Sea to Sea, and run to and fro to ſeek the word of the Lord, and ſhall not find it.</hi> But alaſs! under the plentiful means of grace we enjoy, how ſlight ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes keep us from them? As in Summer, its too hot, in Winter, its too cold; In Spring its ſic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ly, and in Harveſt they are too buſie. The way is farr, or the weather is foul, or elſe ſay people, I like not the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, He is a dry fellow, He is a Presbyterian or an Independent, or this, or that. By theſe and ſuch like ſimple and ſilly pretences Satan deludes the Souls of men, and keeps them from hearing, when they have the opportunity put into their hands. But let ſuch remember, <hi>Thomas</hi> was but once abſent, and that not <note place="margin">Iohn 20. 24.</note> willingly, and not knowing that Chriſt would then appear, and he was like to have loſt the confirmation of the Article of the Reſurrection; ſo may we be wanting, when that may be ſpoken, which we may never again be told of, perhaps that truth which might have done us eternal good. This is the firſt advice that I ſhall in anſwering the queſtion fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned leave with you. <hi>Neglect not ſo great ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 2. 3.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, Apply what's ſpoken to thy ſelf, Let <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> the Preachers words take hold upon thee. We are naturally well pleaſed when Preachers words take hold on others, as <hi>Herod</hi> when <hi>John</hi> Preached a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Phariſees, but we are loath they ſhould come too cloſe to our ſelves. When <hi>John</hi> came to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:135400:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> touch <hi>Herod</hi> about the matter of <hi>Herodias,</hi> and meets with his beloved ſin, <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> ſhall loſe his head. Let us then be leſs inquiſitive concerning others, and apply what's ſpoken to our ſelves. Moſt men ſay as <hi>Peter</hi> of <hi>John, What ſhall this man do?</hi> but let us <note place="margin">John 21. 21. 2 Sam. 7. 18. Mat. 19. 16.</note> ſay as <hi>David, Lord who am I?</hi> or as that youngman in the Goſpel, to Chriſt, not what ſhall others do, <hi>But Lord what ſhall I do?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Be contented to be convinced of the evil of your <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> own ways. Suffer the word of Reproof. This is a harder matter than men are aware of, to be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to be reproved. The moſt of hearers are like Thiſtles, you may ſtroak them upward without danger, but preſs them downward, and immediatly they offend. Preach Goſpel-truths and no more, a wicked man likes it. A Carnal heart can be content to hear of Chriſt and of grace; The ſtony hearers <note place="margin">Luke 8. 13.</note> receive this word with joy: But once tell him, This way of wickedneſs is unlawful, this or that profitable ſin muſt be left, this gain or pleaſure parted with, Then, away with theſe fellows, Theſe are they which trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the world, as thoſe unbeleeving Jews ſpoke of the Apoſtles, <hi>They which have turned the whole world</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Acts 17. 6.</note> 
                     <hi>upſide down are come hither alſo.</hi> Its the property of a true beleever to be willing to be told of his faults, that he may amend them; And its the property of an Hypocrite, yea his diſcovery by which he may know himſelf, That he cannot endure to hear of his ſins, becauſe he is not minded to forſake them. <hi>Paul</hi> is accounted an enemy if he ſpeak the truth, and that <note place="margin">Gal. 4. 16.</note> in the eſteem of thoſe who ſometimes could have been content to pull out their own eyes to have done him good.</p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:135400:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p> So <hi>Herod</hi> heard <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> gladly, till he told him him of <hi>Herodias.</hi> Thus are many ſo pleaſed with their ſins, that they are angry with thoſe that ſhew them they are ſins, as that diſtracted man I have read of, Who imagined himſelf a King, in which diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per'd conceit he ſo pleaſed himſelf, That when he was cured, he was diſpleaſed with the Phyſician who reſtored him to his right mind; So is it with Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, who are ſo pleaſed in the ignorance or miſtake of ſome profitable practicals, that they are offended with ſuch, who by a diſcovery of the truth ſhall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceive them.</p>
                  <p>Be perſwaded to accept of Reconciliation offer'd, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> and that upon Gods own terms. He ſends his Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors on this errand to entreat you, and beſeech <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5. 19, 20.</note> you to be reconciled. Have good thoughts then of God and Jeſus Chriſt, for know what was flattering<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpoken of <hi>Julius Caeſar, Nihil obliviſci ſolet niſi injurias,</hi> that he forgot nothing but injuries, is moſt true of God and Jeſus Chriſt, who forget nothing but the ſins of penitent ſupplicants.</p>
                  <p>Having thus diſpatched the Improvement of this truth and occaſion, as they reſpect this City and Congregation, unto whom our Reverend friend was a faithful Paſtor; I ſhall now proceed to ſpeak thoſe things which our dead Brother ſpeaks to us, the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viving diſpenſers of Goſpel myſteries; briefly thus.</p>
                  <p>Walk anſwerably to the immortality of our im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment. Having our hearts and affections ſetled upon things of eternity. This Doctrine hath taught us that the Miniſters imployment is about things that never dy. O How unſuitable a thing it is to have Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in our mouths, and the world in our hearts? Let
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:135400:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> us not live below the word we Preach.</p>
                  <p>God teacheth by precept and example, ſo ſhould <note place="margin">Si vis me fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>re, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendum eſt primum ipſi tibi.</note> Preachers. If you would have another grieve for ſin, you muſt firſt grieve your ſelves, and practiſe that you preſs others too; Its a good rule of an antient, <hi>Cavendum eſt ne admirandae virtutis mali ſumus pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtores.</hi> Look to this, let our lives expreſs our Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, leſt we hear that, Phyſician cure thy ſelf. <note place="margin">Luke 4. 23.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Its a witty obſervation I have read, and I wiſh it were not as true as witty, Some Preachers are ſuch in the Pulpit, that when they are there, its pitty they ſhould ever come forth, and when they are out of the Pulpit, its pitty they ſhould ever come in,</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>—Pudet haec opprobria nobis</l>
                     <l>Et dici potuiſſe, &amp; non potuiſſe reſelli.</l>
                  </q>
                  <l>Ther's truth in this ſad ſtory. O what ſhame</l>
                  <l>That ſuch reproach and unrefuted blame</l>
                  <l>Should ſtain the glory of ſo good a name!</l>
                  <p>Let us labour then (Reverend Fathers, and Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) to manifeſt our ſavouring of eternity by our actions as well as expreſſions, eſpecially by our ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting looſe from, and undervaluing of earthly things. Let us look to this, <hi>Ne ſurgant indocti &amp; rapiant coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum, &amp; nos cum noſtris literis detrudimur in B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrum,</hi> Let not thoſe who comparatively are mean in knowledge compaſs Heaven, and we our ſelves with all our learning prove caſt aways.</p>
                  <p>O let us now learn this leſſon from this our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend deceaſed Fellow-Labourer. Of whom I do boldly affirm upon my own knowledge, that he was exceeding free from that, which is a ſordid thing in
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:135400:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> all Chriſtians, but a moſt indelible blemiſh in the Lords diſpenſers, earthly-mindedneſs, For of him I may ſay, and ſay truly, what was ſpoke of <hi>Luther, Non curabat Aurum,</hi> He uſed, but not loved the world.</p>
                  <p>I know we are all of us exceeding witty to find out arguments to juſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fie that courſe we have a mind unto, and a ſad thing it is that covetouſneſs which is Idolatry, ſhould be accounted provident care and <note place="margin">Col. 3. 5.</note> good Husbandry.</p>
                  <p>We are ready to ſay, as Miniſters we Preach eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, but as men we look to temporals. I grant this, and therefore adde, That its not the having, but the loving, and the inordinate ſeeking after the world, that God condemns. Let us not then deceive our ſelves, for if God condemn the man for his earthly mindedneſs, what will become of the Miniſter with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all his ſpirituals?</p>
                  <p>Suitable to this is that ſtory of an Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Colen,</hi> who marching with his followers in a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like and ſtately equipage, was met by a Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. The Countryman ſmiled, and being asked the cauſe of that incivility, anſwered, That he could not chooſe but ſmile, and did greatly wonder, that the Apoſtles who were themſelves ſo mean and poor, ſhould have ſuch rich, ſtately and magnificent ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors. The Arch Biſhop replyed, that he was a Duke as well as an Arch-Biſhop, and as a Duke was now ſo attended on with that warlike Company. The Country man replyed, that he deſired him to reſolve this queſtion, When my Lord the Duke for his pride ſhall be caſt into Hell, what then will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of my Lord the Arch-Biſhop?</p>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:135400:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p> And indeed Brethren we have need to be warned, becauſe the worlds profits and honours are the moſt powerful temptations, and therefore Satan made it his laſt aſſault againſt Chriſt, by ſhewing him (whom <note place="margin">Mat. 4. 8.</note> he hoped to have found like another man) the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of the world, and the glory thereof. Though Satan herein loſt his labour, yet he prevails thereby too much with many, who with <hi>Balaam</hi> run greedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">Jude 11.</note> after the ways of iniquity, and as <hi>Judas,</hi> even ſell their maſters for pieces of ſilver, and with <hi>Demas,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4. 10.</note> forſake the Goſpel to embrace the preſent world. O the glory of the world! How alluring? the deceivable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Riches! How prevailing? this makes men <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6. 5.</note> kneel down to the devil without a Cuſhion, and think, That gain is godlineſs. <hi>The Labourer is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ibi fas ibi plurima mercis.</hi> Luke 10. 7. Pſal. 35. 27. <hi>Salvian.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>of his Hire,</hi> and he that doth Gods work and truſts him for it, ſhall not want his wages. God is a good Maſter, who delights in the proſperity of his ſervants. An antient ſaid of ſome (O that it might not be tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaid of ſome of us that are here preſent) <hi>Uti volunt Deo, ut fruantur mundo.</hi> They uſe God, that they may enjoy the world. And I have read of a Fryer, that he would alwaies in a counter-feit humility dine upon a Net, till he had gaind the Popedome.</p>
                  <p>Let not then I beſeech you Brethren, our own preferment, credit, maintenance, or any outward ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, be our propoſed aim in our Miniſterial em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment. Let it not be ſaid of any of us, <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam non agnos, Lac non vaccam, Vineam propter vinum, Populum ob praedam petunt.</hi> I will not, I need not Engliſh it, they who know no Latine are too apt to ſpeak it (and O that it might be without cauſe.)
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:135400:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> For ſhould we ſo do, we ſhould fetch our fire from our own Kitchins, which ſhould be lighted at Gods Sanctuary, and thereby turn that, which otherwiſe would be lawful gain, into filthy lucre. No, know there is a more excellent gain, even ſouls. This <hi>Paul</hi> ſought, witneſs that expreſſion, <hi>I ſeek not yours, but you;</hi> and therefore Preachers ſhould ſay as the King of <hi>Sodom</hi> did to <hi>Abraham,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>Da mihi animas, Caetera tolle tibi;</q>
                  <p>Give me the ſouls, take thou the reſt.</p>
                  <p>Let us look up to our Lord and Maſter Jeſus Chriſt, whoſe Embaſſadors, Servants, Meſſengers we pretend we are; and ſince we bear his name, and do his work, its fit we ſhould deſire to have his mind; he ſought not his own, but our advantage, as <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curie</hi> in <hi>Plautus</hi> being transformed into <hi>Soſia.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <l>Etenim vero quoniam formam cepi hujus in me, &amp; ſtatum,</l>
                  <l>Decet &amp; facta mor eſque hujus habere me ſimiles item.</l>
                  <p>Walk we as Chriſt walked. Tread in his ſteps. 1 <hi>John</hi> 2. 6.</p>
                  <p>Let us not do Gods will in our imployment for meat and drink; But let it be our meat and drink to do Gods will. O then Reverend Fathers and Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, let the immortality of our imployment cauſe us to walk anſwerable to eternity. The woman that was clothed with the Sun, had the Moon under her feet, and they who are Gods Agents to trade for Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, ſhould ſcorn the Devils factory for the earth.</p>
                  <p>For if in our hearts and practices we ſerve the world, and yet with our tongues Preach the word,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:135400:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> We may peradventure as <hi>Noahs</hi> Carpenters help to build the Ark, and yet be drowned our ſelves.</p>
                  <p>I now come to the general improvement of this truth, to all of us here preſent.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, ſee the Excellency of the Miniſterial im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment. Its converſant about Eternal things. All other imployments are in and about finite and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral affairs. The work of Lawyers, Phyſicians, all other profeſſions, is bounded within the limits of time; Only the Miniſters work runs parallel with the lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt line of eternity; The word of Chriſt Preached by them being not a finite meſſage, but an <hi>everlaſting Goſpel.</hi> This conſideration I would commend unto <note place="margin">Rev. 14. 6.</note> you, that you that are Hearers may be able to judge, and we that are Preachers may be able to bear thoſe unworthy reproaches, the poyſoned Arrows of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venomed tongues ſet on fire by Hell, that at this day <note place="margin">James 3. 6.</note> are darted againſt the pretious ſervants of God, the faithfull diſpenſers of his word.</p>
                  <p>What though prophane Epicures, ſcoffing <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maels,</hi> mocking <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>chols,</hi> furious, frantick, fiery Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nioniſts, like <hi>Sampſons</hi> Foxes, though looking con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary ways, yet linked together by the tayls with fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brands, <note place="margin">Judges 15.</note> all joyn together to caſt reproach and dirt in the face of Gods ſervants? Yet know, that the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of our imployment, the eternity of our work, may ſupport our ſpirits againſt all thoſe diſgraces, that the unreſtrained wickedneſs, or wittineſs of men unjuſtly lay upon us.</p>
                  <p>Now as to theſe reproaches I ſhall treſpaſs yet fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon your patience while I ſhall mind you of</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Some obſervations concerning them.</item>
                     <item>2. Rules to direct us in our carriage under them.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="1">1. Obſervations.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:135400:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> 1. Its no new thing. <hi>So perſecuted they the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 5. 12.</note> 
                     <hi>that were before.</hi> If the Jews call Chriſt <note place="margin">Mat. 10. 25.</note> 
                     <hi>Beelzebub,</hi> who came to deſtroy Satan; ſhall we now wonder if any call thoſe Miniſters Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, that have and alwaies do oppoſe Anti-Chriſt? If the Galatians who would at firſt have <note place="margin">Gal. 4. 15, 16.</note> pluckt out their eyes, yet afterwards eſteem <hi>Paul</hi> their enemy; ſhall we now admire that ſome, who have been formerly forward favourers of faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Preachers, are now become profeſs'd revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers? Whence comes this alteration? Not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Paul</hi> was changed; No, he ſpake ſtill the <note place="margin">Gal. 3. 1.</note> ſame truth: But becauſe the Galatians, bewitched by falſe teachers, were fallen from that truth they formerly pretended a love unto.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Its no ſad thing as to thoſe who are reproched, but rather a cauſe of joy; <hi>Rejoyce and be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding glad,</hi> ſaith our Saviour, <hi>for great is your</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 5. 12.</note> 
                     <hi>reward.</hi> For certainly it is not any perſonal quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel that men have with Miniſters, that is the cauſe they diſlike and vilifie them; No, but its becauſe they Preach the truth; and therefore its the truth of God they hate, more than it is the Miniſter that Preached it. For, <hi>Propter quod unum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quodque eſt tale, illud eſt magis tale.</hi> What cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes the hatred is moſt hated.</p>
                  <p>Chriſt ſaith, Woe be to him of whom every one ſpeaks well; and we may adde, Woe be to him of <note place="margin">Luke 6. 26</note> whom every one ſpeaks ill; but to be ſpoken e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil <note place="margin">Vituperari â malis eſſe laudari.</note> of by thoſe, who are themſelves evil, is no diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Its no hurtful or dangerous thing, and ſo not much to be regarded, but to be paſs'd by with a ſilent neglect.</p>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:135400:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>The generous ſteed neglects contemptible bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>They hurt themſelves moſt, by that which they think to diſgrace others by. The ſtones they throw fall down upon their own heads. And how think you will Jeſus Chriſt look upon them at the laſt day, who to diſgrace his ſervants, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe <note place="margin">The name of Prieſt properly belongs to Chriſt, who ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſed, and is as an Honour appropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated to all Saints un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, and not to Miniſters. Rev. 1. 6.</note> his own Title, and by way of ſcorn call Miniſters by that name, by which Chriſt is moſt comfortably to be known, <hi>viz.</hi> By the name of Prieſts?</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Its not alwaies a ſign that that is evill which is ſpoken againſt, For we read what was ſaid of the Chriſtian Religion, that <note n="*" place="margin">Acts 28. 22. James 1. 26.</note> 
                     <hi>this ſect is every where ſpoken againſt:</hi> No, but its a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt ſign of evill in thoſe that ſo do, and we may eaſily ſee the rancour and bitterneſs of mens minds, by the utterance of their tongues. A pimpled face diſcovers a diſtemper'd Liver; A ſtinking breath, corrupted lungs; A railing tongue makes manifeſt a wicked, rotten, envious, naughty heart; therefore St. <hi>James</hi> gives this character of an hypocritical profeſſor, That he bridleth not his tongue, though he ſeem to be religious, but therein deceives his heart, and therein is his Religion vain; whence it is evident, That Rayling and Religion do not, cannot, dwell together. Where then is their Religion that make it their buſineſs to rail at, and revile the Lords Meſſengers?</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Having thus acquainted you with theſe obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations, I ſhall endeavour to make them uſeful to all, but eſpecially to us Miniſters, by perſwading the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of theſe two Rules.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:135400:23"/> 1. Indeavour to prevent all occaſion from thoſe that wait for it, that they may not have their mouths opened againſt us juſtly. There are a generation of men in this Nation, in this City, in this place (happily) that look for Miniſters haltings. Let us then walk more circumſpectly, and take care that we <hi>give no offence, either to</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10. 32. Acts 24. 16.</note> 
                     <hi>the Jew or Gentile, or to the Church of God;</hi> to thoſe that own us or diſown us. As <hi>Paul</hi> did, ſo let us exerciſe our ſelves to keep alwaies a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience void of offence, both towards God and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards men,</hi> and then, <hi>Non offendunt obloquenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um verba, quem propria non inquinaverit con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientia,</hi> Reproches of revilers will never harm, where mens own conſciences are not defiled. As much as its poſſible, Let us live peaceably with all men. But know, that Peace muſt not be bought with the loſs of Truth. If men are our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies for truths ſake, <hi>Valeant,</hi> Let them be ſo. That mans friendſhip is not worth the keeping, where the proſtituting of Truth muſt be the price of it.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Anſwer not reviling with reviling, railing with railing. The Spirit of man luſts to revenge. <note place="margin">James 4. 5.</note> But let not us do to them as they have done to us. But let us bleſs where they curſe, and herein ſhew our ſelves Chriſts Diſciples. Miniſters muſt <note place="margin">Mat. 5. 44.</note> expect when they Preach well to hear ill, and when they bring the Goſpel of ſalvation, to be accounted the filth and off ſcouring of the world. <note place="margin">1 Cor. 4. 13.</note> But whatever undeſerved reproachings men caſt upon us, Let us take them up as our Crown, and with <hi>Paul</hi> rejoyce in our very ſuffrings, in that <hi>we</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Col. 1. 24.</note>
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:135400:24"/> 
                     <hi>fill up that which is behind of the afflictions of Chriſt for his bodies ſake, which is the Church.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And to eaſe our ſelves, Let us not as the men of the world do, vent our paſſions to men, but our caſe to God, and ſpread ſuch revilings before the Lord, as <hi>Hezechiah</hi> did the railing Letter of <note place="margin">Iſa. 37. 14.</note> 
                     <hi>Senacherib,</hi> with this prayer, which our Saviour taught us, <hi>Father forgive them, they know not what they do.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The laſt uſe I ſhall make of this truth, That though <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Preachers dye, yet Sermons live, is to perſwade you, while you have time, and while you are call'd by the word, to let your hearts anſwer that call, that you may be taken hold on by Gods word for good. Labour for an intereſt in God by Chriſt, the enjoyment of whom will be your chiefeſt good. <hi>This is life eternal</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">John 17. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>to know thee the only true God, and whom thou haſt ſent Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> God is the only <hi>ſummum bonum,</hi> chief good, He is <hi>optimum,</hi> the beſt, and ſo can ſuit, he is <hi>maximum bonum,</hi> the greateſt, and can ſatisfy our deſires.</p>
                  <p>Be prevailed withall to ſtudy Jeſus Chriſt more, and in him your own immortaliy, and labour after a cleerer knowledge of eternal Excellencies. For cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly had we Heaven more in our eyes, we ſhould have it more in our hearts. I have read that the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of a Philoſopher concerning the contempt of life, prevailed with the Mileſian Virgins to deſtroy themſelves, and of <hi>Cleombrotus,</hi> who reading <hi>Plato</hi> of immortality, threw himſelf headlong that he might enjoy it. And ſhall diſcourſes of Heaven and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality work nothing upon us? O that we could
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:135400:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſee Heaven as it is, then ſhould we be willing to leave Earth. When <hi>Paul</hi> had been rapt up into Heaven, and had ſome taſte of the inexpreſſible joys and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights thereof, then was he willing to depart, and <note place="margin">Phil. 1. 23.</note> to be with Chriſt, which was beſt of all.</p>
                  <p>Though <hi>Paul</hi> while here, was with Chriſt, and Chriſt was with him, between whom there was a ſpiritual union and Communion; Yet in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of what he expected in Heaven, he reckons him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf while in the body, <hi>abſent from the Lord.</hi> Here <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5. 6.</note> we enjoy as it were the Crums of grace; Heaven is a full Table, Whereat though all ſhall not fare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, yet every one ſhall have his full portion. As <note place="margin">Exod. 16. 18.</note> the gatherers of <hi>Manna,</hi> who had not all equal, yet had all ſufficient.</p>
                  <p>Our underſtanding here in compariſon of what it will be, is no more than the eye of a Bat to an Eagle, the creeping of a Snayl to the flying of a Swallow. And ſo are our poſſeſſions and enjoyments. Here we have mixt, and at beſt ſhort and fading pleaſures, <hi>But when we awake at the reſurrection we ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Pſ. 17. 15.</note> 
                     <hi>with Gods Image, with whom is fulneſs of joy,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Pſ. 16. 11.</note> 
                     <hi>and at whoſe right hand there are pleaſures for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The knowledge of this may leſſon our grief for friends, who are by death parted from us. Such friends as dye in the Lord, they are no loſers; They go to <note place="margin">Rev. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 13 Joſh 7. 25. Judges 2. 5. Rev. 21. 4.</note> a bleſſed, to a better place; from the Vally of <hi>Achor</hi> and <hi>Bochim,</hi> from trouble and weeping, to fulneſs of joy, where all tears are wiped away, where is no more death, or ſorrow, or crying, or pain. To this place of joy, this our Reverend Friend is gone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, who hath left us behind in the Camp, the place
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:135400:25"/> of travail, and hath aſcended the Capitol, the place of Triumph. He hath not loſt, but gained by his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moval.</p>
                  <p>Its obſerved, that by Gods appointment, when a <note place="margin">Deut. 15. 13.</note> Captive <hi>Iſraelite</hi> was Manumiſſed, the Maſter might not ſend him away empty, but was to furniſh him with a ſupply of neceſſaries, and that liberally; thus doth God with the ſouls of his elect, when he frees them from the captivity of ſin, by grace in their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, he adorns them; So when he delivers them <note place="margin">Ezech. 16. 7.</note> out of the Priſons of their bodies by death, He makes their Spirits fully perfect. And therefore our grief for this our friend may be the leſs. Yet when we <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 23.</note> conſider his Orphan family, we muſt needs grieve his death as their great loſs, for whom yet, in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things, his provident care hath not been wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, He having left each of them ſo much, that they will not be beholden to their enemies, and yet ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, that for their education and breeding up, they will need the reſpect and kindneſs of their friends. But this hath he left his children, better than all outward portions, the bleſſing of God, and his ingagement to be their Father.</p>
                  <p>For though grace be perſonal, and corruption be Natural Parents communicate their Natures, God His grace; Circumciſed Parents, beget uncircumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Children, and winnowed Corn brings forth Chaff; though when <hi>Poetae naſcuntur non fiunt,</hi> Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets are born ſo, not made, <hi>Chriſtiani fiunt non naſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuntur,</hi> Chriſtians are made and not born; Yet a great mercy it is to be the iſſue of a believing Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent.</p>
                  <p>Many prayers made for them, Many promiſes
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:135400:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> made to them; that though Father and Mother for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake <note place="margin">Pſal. 68. 5.</note> them, yet God will not leave ſuch friendleſs, but will take them up. Yea God is the God of the ſeed <note place="margin">Acts 2. 39.</note> of believers, as well as of themſelves. To end all. This our deceaſed Brother was a wiſe dealer; whereas moſt men deal with the world, and Satan, for plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, whoſe end proves painful, and profits, that have no true advantage; Yet he was by God made wiſe to trade with and for God. He hath bought the truth and not ſold it; He hath broke Chriſts bread, and it hath multiplyed in his hands; He hath caſt out his Net, and it hath proſpered, and ſouls by him have been turned to righteouſneſs, and therein hath tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for himſelf, and gained full and laſting pleaſures, durable and real profits, even Heaven it ſelf, where he now enjoys the reward of Gods promiſe, and ſhines as a Star in the Firmament; and truly (I ſpeak <note place="margin">Dan. 12. 2.</note> it without flattery or vanity) for the general courſe of his life, for the profitableneſs and ſucceſs of his Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, for the Comfort, Peace, and manifeſtation of Gods love and ſupport, which he had in his ſick Bed, and to his end, every one of us may ſay and pray</p>
                  <q>Sic mihi contingat vivere, ſicque mori.</q>
                  <p>O that our lives and ends might be ſuch.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall cloſe this diſcourſe with this Obſervation. A Gentleman took order before his death, that this Epitaph ſhould be engraven on his Tomb, <hi>Here lyes the Friend of Sir</hi> Philip Sydney. If now it were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed ſo great an honour, to be, and be reputed the friend of an earthly man, How much greater Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:135400:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> have all believers, (This our deceaſed friend in particular) to be called, as <hi>Abraham</hi> was, the Friend of God? ſo that on the Tomb of this our Reverend Brother, whoſe Funeral we have now ſolemnized, may be truly Ingraven, <hi>Here lyeth the dutiful Servant, the faithful Miniſter, the choice friend of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>Soli Deo Gloria.</closer>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:135400:26"/>
                  <p>AN EXHORTATION IMMEDIATLY FOLLOWING THE SERMON THAT Was Preached at the Funeral of Mr. <hi>SAMUEL OLIVER</hi> Paſtor at WELLS.</p>
                  <p>Written (upon requeſt) with ſome little altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of, and additions, here and there, unto, what was at firſt haſtily delivered.</p>
                  <p>Wherein the thing intended is, in ſum, this, to lay cloſe to our hearts this truth, That affliction, and in ſpecial, the loſs of Friends (more eſpecially of Miniſters) is not to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergone ſtoutly without ſenſe; nor to be born frowardly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out patience; nor to be paſs'd over lightly without profit.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>James. 5. 11.</bibl>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Ye have heard of the patience of</hi> Job, <hi>and have ſeen the end of the Lord.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. W.</hi> for <hi>John Place,</hi> and are to be Sold at his Shop at Furnivals Inn-Gate in <hi>Holburn.</hi> 1653.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="exhortation">
                  <pb facs="tcp:135400:27"/>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:135400:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>An Exhortation following the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon that was Preached at the Funeral of Mr. <hi>Samuel Oliver</hi> Paſtor at <hi>Wels,</hi> that, in a great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation both of Miniſters and people then met together, there might be a more profitable uſe made of the preſent occaſion.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough you have been ſomewhat extraordinarily deteined already, out of a willingneſs to ſet on good inſtruction, upon ſo moving an occaſion, yet ſuffer me to be a Suter unto you (Honoured, Reverend, and Beloved) for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing of your patience, while I adde a little more to what hath been already ſpoken, concerning our deceaſed Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who was for you of this place, a faithful Miniſter of Chriſt <note n="(a)" place="margin">Col. 1. 7.</note>; And that the rather, becauſe it is very ſuitable, that he that was ſo abundant an Inſtructor, ſhould have his Funeral ſolemnized with more abundant inſtruction; which though now it may ſeem very tedious, yet you may be pleaſed to remember, that when a dear Friend is to take a long Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, all his Friends (thinking, that perhaps they ſhall never ſee him more) are willing to allot a longer time to take their leave of him; Our dear Friend is gone a long journey, to his long home <note n="(b)" place="margin">Eccl. 12. 5.</note>, Let us crave pardon therefore, if we be longer in parting with him, and imparting to you what we deſire ſhould be profitable upon ſo obſervable a providence.</p>
                  <p>But to come to that which I intend to ſay, <hi>(wherein I humbly deſire, and deſire to have deſired, that divine aſſiſtance whereof there is ſo great need and uſe)</hi> that I may therein preſcribe unto my ſelf ſome bounds, I ſhall entreat you to read with me</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Job</hi> 1. 20, 21, 22.</bibl>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Then</hi> Job <hi>aroſe, and rent his mantle, and ſhaved his head, and fell down upon the ground, and worſhipped;</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>And ſaid, Naked came I out of my mothers womb, and naked ſhall I return thither: the Lord gave, and the Lord hath taken away, bleſſed be the name of the Lord.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>In all this</hi> Job <hi>ſinned not, nor charged God fooliſhly.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <p>The Exhortation (in which I ſhall have reſpect all along unto theſe words) I branch out into three Rules.</p>
                  <div n="1" type="rule">
                     <head>The firſt Rule. <hi>Seriouſly take to heart</hi> (I exhort you) <hi>every ſpecial hand of God.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>This the Scripture requires <note n="(a)" place="margin">Eccl. 7. 14.</note>, and complains much of the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <note n="(b)" place="margin">Iſa 5. 12. &amp; 42. 25. Jer. 5. 3.</note>. And this is (in the firſt place) preſented unto us in <hi>Jobes</hi> exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who <hi>aroſe,</hi> as being ſtirr'd and much mov'd by many moſt ſad Meſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:135400:28"/> and by the laſt (that brought him news of the loſs of his children) moſt, <hi>and rent his mantle, or robe,</hi> as mourn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ng <hi>Thamar</hi> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d hers <note n="(c)" place="margin">2 Sam. 13. 18, 19.</note>, and <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>haved his head,</hi> that being another cuſtom that mourners uſed in thoſe Countries <note n="(d)" place="margin">Jer. 7. 29.</note>, <hi>and fell down upon the ground,</hi> which is another ſign of a grieved mind, taking greatly to heart Gods hand. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>2. 16, 17.</p>
                     <p>Nor is <hi>Job</hi> to be blamed for making ſo much adoe; for it is ſaid after this, <hi>In all this</hi> Job <hi>ſinned not.</hi> v. 22. It is not a Sin, but a thing ſuitable to Gods ſervants, and their Rules, to be affected with affliction, that thereby all men may ſee they do not <hi>deſpiſe it. Prov.</hi> 3. 11.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>In ſpecial,</hi> we are to take to heart Gods hand in dying perſons, and to be mov'd with ſorrow in houſes of mourning, where the <note n="(e)" place="margin">Eccl. 7. 2, 3.</note> heart, by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made ſadder, is made better; <hi>More eſpecially,</hi> the death of righteous perſons, and men merciful (as their Father which is in Heaven is merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful) is to lie cloſe upon our Spirits; God lays it to mens charge, that they lay not this to their heart <note n="(a)" place="margin">Iſa. 57. 1.</note>, and that upon a ſpec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>al reaſon, to wit, becauſe the <hi>righteous are taken away from the evill to come,</hi> (as people catch up their children, when there is an eminent and imminent danger,) now they be very inconſiderate, who make nothing of that perſonal mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, which is a preſage of publike miſery.</p>
                     <p>But <hi>moſt eſpecially,</hi> the death of publike perſons, and (to ſpeak to the preſent purpoſe) of faithful Miniſters, is to be lamented, and laid to heart.</p>
                     <div type="reasons">
                        <head>And that for theſe Reaſons.</head>
                        <p n="1">1. <hi>In regard of themſelves.</hi> To ſhew our due eſtimation of them, (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Rule <note n="(b)" place="margin">Phil. 2. 29. 1 Theſ. 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>3.</note>, and that we looked upon them as perſons, in whom we enjoyed a kind of bleſſedneſs when we had them <note n="(c)" place="margin">Gal. 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>5.</note>; Now, How can we ſay, they are eſteemed, who depart without being deſired, as that wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked King <hi>Jehoram</hi> did <note n="(d)" place="margin">2 Chro. 21. 20.</note>, or that they depart as perſons deſired, who depart without being lamented? See <hi>John</hi> 11. 35, 36. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 35. 25.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. <hi>In regard of the Church.</hi> The ſame Church compaſſion, which prays that labourers may be ſent out <note n="(e)" place="margin">Mat. 9. 36, 37.</note>, mourns when they be call'd in, never to labour more.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. <hi>Out of love to the Land, and the preſervation of the State.</hi> It may ſeem to ſome an unpleaſing Paradox, to ſay that the Church is the Guard of the Common-wealth; yet was it not without juſt cauſe, that the <hi>ſupreme power</hi> ſometime ſaid to a Prophet, <hi>O my Father, my Father, the charet of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and the horſemen thereof</hi> 
                           <note n="(f)" place="margin">2 Kings 2. 12. 2 Kings 13. 14.</note>; can any love the State, and not be heartily ſorry that the <hi>Militia</hi> of the State, the <hi>Sacra Militia,</hi> the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical Army, or the Army of the Angels of the Churches, at the head of which God is <note n="(g)" place="margin">Mat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>8. 20.</note>, ſhould be, (eſpecially more eminently, or more immaturely) diminiſhed? their Arms (Beloved) (think it not fondneſs to ſpeak as the Scripture ſpeaks) as they are mighty <hi>through God;</hi> ſo they are mighty <hi>with God</hi> 
                           <note n="(a)" place="margin">Hoſ. 12. 3. Gen. 20. 7.</note>, ſo mighty, that we may ſay (in a ſober ſenſe, and with humble hearts) that God cannot do what (according to his revealed will) he would do, becauſe they will not let him alone to do it. <hi>Exod.</hi> 32. 20.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. <hi>Out of Love to God himſelf.</hi> For what are Miniſters appointed for,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:135400:28" rendition="simple:additions"/> but to <hi>bear up the Name of God before the Sons of men?</hi> And, ſhould it not <note place="margin">Acts 9. 15.</note> much grieve us to ſee any of them lye in the duſt, who are the appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted inſtruments to keep the name of God from lying in the duſt?</p>
                        <p>Hence it is that we thus mou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>n. Indeed Prieſts (and ſometime Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets) are forbidden to mourn, (upon ſpecial accounts) in the old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament; but in the new Teſtament we find <hi>Paul</hi> profeſſing ſorrow upon ſorrow, if <hi>Epaphroditus,</hi> (that faithful, and life neglecting labourer for the work of Chriſt) had not been recovered from his ſickneſs <note n="(c)" place="margin">Phil. 2. 27, 30.</note>.</p>
                        <p>O that we could lay cloſe to our hearts, the want of laying cloſe to our hearts the ſad-preſaging death of Gods ſervants! what's become of the ſweet Spirit of thoſe Primitive Chriſtians, who <hi>ſorrowed moſt of all,</hi> (were extremely ſorry for this) that <hi>Paul</hi> had ſaid they ſhould <hi>See his face no more? Acts</hi> 20. 38. And we are ſure, that when once a Miniſter of Chriſt is returned to his duſt, we ſhall ſee his face no more among the inhabitants of the world; either therefore thoſe melting Chriſtians were much mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken when their ſorrow was ſo great, or elſe we may bluſh, while ours is ſo little.</p>
                        <p>To conclude this firſt Rule, whereſoever there is any houſe of mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, we ſhall do well to remember, that an advantage is put into our hands, for the bettering of our hearts. <note n="[a]" place="margin">Eccl. 7. 3.</note> As (therefore) Phyſicians and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natomiſts, adde to their art, by diſſections, and prying into all the parts of dead perſons; ſo let us labour to be gainers, to adde to our Spiritual ſtock, and the art of living and dying well, by taking to heart, diſtinctly pondering upon, and even anatomiſing, divine providences in the death of any, but of thoſe that be faithful and fear God above many, much more, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 7. 2.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="rule">
                     <head>The ſecond Rule. <hi>Have reverent thoughts of every more heavy hand of God.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>For we may not be ſo taken up with our mourning for men, as to forget our worſhipping of God. This alſo <hi>Job</hi> doth here preach unto us by his practice, who did not as they who curſe their King and their God, and look upward (in that mood) <note n="(a)" place="margin">Iſa. 8. 21.</note>, but fell down upon the ground, and ſo fell-down as that he alſo <hi>worſhipped.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Which worſhipping contains two things in it.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. <hi>A ſubmiſſion to God;</hi> ſuch as was in <hi>Aaron,</hi> when he held his peace, even when his two Sons were ſlain both at once <note n="(b)" place="margin">Levit. 10. 3.</note> 
                        <hi>Worſhipping</hi> and <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi> reverence and impatience are two oppoſite things. The third Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that fell down upon his knees before <hi>Elijas,</hi> ſhewed by that geſture, that he meant not to fight <note n="(c)" place="margin">2 Kings 1. 13.</note>, but ſubmitted, that he might have quarter.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. <hi>A celebration of him;</hi> with his worſhipping there is a <hi>ſaying</hi> v. 21. the cloſe whereof is, <hi>Bleſſed be the name of the Lord.</hi> O, How the Devils ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation was croſs'd in this bleſſing of God by an undone <hi>Job!</hi> That Accuſer and Lyar pronounced confidently, that if God did touch him in all he had, he would curſe him to his face <note n="(d)" place="margin">Job. 10. 11.</note>, but his holineſs out-laſts his Hedge, and his reverence of God ſurvives the ruins of his State and Family; When Satan took away all that <hi>Job</hi> had, his meaning was not to make him (a <hi>Beggar</hi> that was to him as it was to <hi>Haman</hi> to lay hands
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:135400:29"/> on <hi>Mordecai</hi> alone <hi>(e),</hi> the thing he aimed at was to make him a <hi>Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemer,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Heſter 3. 6.</note> to curſe God; but he deceived the Devil, and when all's gone, Behold he bleſſeth him altogether <note n="(a)" place="margin">Num. 24. 11.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Which commends unto us this inſtruction, in our greateſt affliction, to wit, not only to carry our ſelves therein as Gods <hi>Subjects,</hi> and crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and not ſpeak againſt him, but as Gods <hi>Advocates,</hi> and plead for him. <note n="(b)" place="margin">Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hem. 9. 33.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Q. <hi>But, How may that be done?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> By taking <hi>Jobes</hi> courſe in this place, that is, by gathering up Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, wherewithall to do it.</p>
                     <div type="arguments">
                        <head>Here are two.</head>
                        <p n="1">1. His native nakedneſs, or the condition of all men according to the Law of Nature, <hi>Naked came I out of my Mothers womb</hi> (without Sheep, or Oxen, or Camels, or Houſe, or Children) and (when I die) <hi>naked ſhall I return thither;</hi> whither is that? Sure, Not into his Mothers womb again that firſt bare him, (we account it a great weakneſs in <hi>Nicodemus</hi> to ask that queſtion; <hi>Can a man enter the ſecond time into his Mothers womb?</hi> John 3. 4.) but <hi>thither,</hi> that is to the Grave. This is confirmed by the wiſe mans expreſſion <hi>(Eccl.</hi> 5. 15.) <hi>As he came forth out of his Mothers womb, naked</hi> 
                           <note place="margin">Vide Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerum &amp; Bezam in loc.</note> 
                           <hi>ſhall he return to go as he came.</hi> As he came naked out of his Mothers womb into the world, So ſhall he go naked out of the world into his Grave, <hi>And ſhall take nothing of his labour, which he may carry away in his hand.</hi> Unto this interpretation further ſtrength will be added, if we conſider that <hi>Jobes</hi> purpoſe is not to inſiſt on the place whither he goes, when he <note place="margin">Jun. &amp; Trem. in loc.</note> goes out of the world, but the manner how he goes out, to wit, naked, as he came in, <hi>For we brought nothing into this world, and it is certain we can carry nothing out.</hi> 1 Tim. 6. 7.</p>
                        <p>It is obſerved alſo, that in this <hi>(whither). Job</hi> doth as it were point with the finger unto the earth on which he was now fallen, as the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <note place="margin">
                              <hi>Magna Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens terra eſt</hi> Ovid. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamor. <hi>Magna conſolatio eſt in rerum amiſſione illa tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra ad me moria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere quibus nos contigit res quas perdidimus non habuiſſe</hi> Greg. Moral in Job. Lib. 2.</note> verſe ſhews.</p>
                        <p>However, Its agreed on by all that by <hi>(thither)</hi> he means the Earth or the Grave, and ſo we may thus reſolve the words; <hi>Naked came I out of the womb of my earthly Mother, and naked ſhall I return into the womb of my Mother Earth.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>A great argument for patience, it <hi>being a great comfort</hi> (as one ſays) <hi>in the loſs of all, to call to mind thoſe times wherein we had nothing of that which we have now laſt.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>No man brought any thing into the world with him, when he was born, and if he have never ſo much here, and it all continue with him, yet he ſhall not take it away with him when he dyes; Then, the queſtion to the richeſt man is, <hi>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>hoſe ſhall th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ſe things be which thou haſt provided?</hi> Luke 12. 20. for thine they ſhall not be; the proviſion is thine, the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, other mens, <hi>Our works follow us,</hi> Revel. 14. 13. Not our wealth. Our earthly eſtates had a beg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nning, and muſt have an end. Suppoſe they be taken away from us, before we be taken away from them, that breaks no ſquare between God and his Children; There is more love between that bleſſed God, and his ſincere Servants, than to differ about ſo ſmall matters.</p>
                        <pb n="49" facs="tcp:135400:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                        <p> We ſhall do well to improve this argument, and to bethink our ſelves whether the ground of impatience, be not a fancy of a kind of eternity in our earthly enjoyments, while we are apt to think, we were. Heirs, and ſo had them when we came into the world, and our hei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s ſhall have them (and we in our Heirs) when we go out of the world. Herein if God croſs us, and take what we do ſo much reckon upon from us and ours, then, we complain bitterly, and ſtrive much with God, for want of ſtudying well <hi>Jobes</hi> Sermon, and taking off from our hearts, the grief of our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs by providence, by the ſerious thought of our nakedneſs by nature both in our birth and at our death.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. <hi>The ſecond Argument</hi> is drawn from the propriety that God hath in our eſtates, and the perſons alſo belonging to us, and thereupon the juſtice of his adminiſtration, while he diſpoſeth as he pleaſeth of them, expreſſed in theſe word<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>, <hi>The Lord gave, and the Lord hath taken away.</hi> He doth not ſay; The Lord gave, and the Devill hath taken away, or the <hi>Chaldeans</hi> and <hi>Sobeans</hi> have taken away, though that were true enough, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>t was not good enough for a <hi>Job</hi> to ſay, <hi>But the Lord gives and takes,</hi> wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ch t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ue doctrine brings in this good concluſion; therefore, I have no right to complain now all is gone; for, <hi>Is it not lawful for God to do what he will with his own?</hi> Mat. 20. 15. Sweet is the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Gregory</hi> in his mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>als on this place. It might happily have been looked upon as a lamentable thing, if God had given, and the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my had taken away, but when God takes away, every mans mouth is ſtop'd; for <hi>[ſua recepit, non noſtra abſtulit] He hath not taken away ours, but taken again his own;</hi> we ſay (indeed) <hi>my bread,</hi> and <hi>my water,</hi> and <hi>my fleſh</hi> 
                           <note n="(a)" place="margin">1 Sam. 25. 11.</note>, my Houſe, and my Lands, my Son, my Daughter: but alas, we are but poſſeſſors and Stewards, God is the Lord and the owner. Its our wiſdom and our righteouſneſs to ſay every one of us, If God take away mine, (any of mine, all of mine) he takes away his own, for my own are his own. Bleſſed therefore be his Name; Magnified for ever be his ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, his Soveraignty. He doth no more than I deſerve, if I conſider my own Sin; He doth no more than he may juſtly do, if I look to his So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty.</p>
                        <p>O that in all the diſaſters of providence, we could take <hi>Jobes</hi> way of patience; which is, not to ſeek out arguments to aggravate the affliction, but to juſtifie that God that afflicts.</p>
                        <p>Q. But, am I bound to ſit down and thank God, for that he hath undone me, and ſtrip'd me of all my comforts?</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Anſ.</hi> Its one thing to thank God for doing ſuch a thing (as if it were a benefit to have it done) Another, to bleſs God when it is done (as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing it a righteous thing in him to do it;) I am bound to bleſs God if he take all away, that is, to give him therein the honour of his juſtice and Soveraign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>y; but I am not to give thanks for affliction, that is, <hi>barely for the evil of affliction,</hi> (I may thank my ſelf for that <note n="(b)" place="margin">Jer. 2. 17. Hoſ. 13. 9.</note>, (yet I may and ſhould thank God for the love from whence it ariſeth, and for the good that God intendeth in it, and promiſeth to work by it; yea I have reaſon to thank God, even for the grief and bitterneſs of affliction alſo
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:135400:30" rendition="simple:additions"/> as it is a neceſſary and effectual furtherance of that ſpiritual good, which God in his Fatherly corrections aimeth at.</p>
                        <p>So men thank the Phyſician and pay him too, not becauſe his Phyſick was bitter, but becauſe health is ſweet; yea they think themſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding to him, for putting ſo much bitterneſs into the medicine as was neceſſary for a ſound and through cure of the diſeaſe.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="rule">
                     <head>The third Rule.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Adde not Sin to affliction, nor diſcontent to diſasters.</hi> Be not worſe for Gods hand; let not affliction draw forth thy corruption (unleſs it be to expel it, as launcing &amp; Tents bring out the corrupt matter of a feſtered Ulcer) but let it exerciſe and ſet a work thy grace; chiding ordinarily ſtirs up choler, but in prudent men it calls in patience, and makes their moderation the better known to all men; when all's hot about them, <note place="margin">Peranti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periſtaſni.</note> they are the colder. <hi>Job</hi> (here) is that wiſe and well tempered man, who rents his mantle, ſhaves his head, and ſorroweth much; <hi>but in all this</hi> Job <hi>ſinned not.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Firſt, his Oxen and Aſſes were taken away, and his ſervants ſlain by the <hi>Sabaeans</hi> ver. 14. 15. Immediatly after that, he heard that the fire of God fallen from Heaven, had burn'd up his Sheep and his ſervants v. 16. Upon that comes the news that the <hi>Caldeans</hi> were fallen upon the Camels, and had carried them away and ſlain the ſervants <hi>ver.</hi> 17. And laſtly, that the Houſe was fallen upon his Children, while they were fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting together, and that they were dead, <hi>ver.</hi> 18. 19. <hi>Yet in all this,</hi> in all theſe calamities <note n="(a)" place="margin">Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer.</note>, in this whole buſineſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <note n="(b)" place="margin">Vata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blus. Mercer.</note>, in al his demeanour and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage in the midſt and height of this manifold affl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ction, he ſinned not <hi>(in heart) or charged God fooliſhly (in word)</hi> (as ſome diſtinguiſh it.)</p>
                     <p>O, How much may God do to a good man, to a man grown in good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, before he will g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ve him an ill word, or entertain an ill thought of him? Not to ſin in all his carriage after all theſe calamities, this is a patience that Honours Heaven, and juſtifies Gods teſtimony of <hi>Job</hi> ver. 8. That makes Hell aſhamed; for the Devil ſaid he would curſe God v. 11. That makes the world wonder, and ſtill talk of <hi>the patience of Job</hi> 
                        <note n="(c)" place="margin">Jam. 5. 11.</note>, and declares to all the ſolicitous ſervants of God, what a prevai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling thing the Grace of God is, for the maſtering of all impetuous and rebellious affections, in the moſt irritating afflictions; I ſay it is ſo <hi>[bona ſi ſua norint]</hi> if they be careful to improve their grace, and put it to its utmoſt ſtrength.</p>
                     <p>Now, that we may not adde ſin, nor ſuffer our corrupt affections to mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiny againſt God in the day of our trouble, and the anguiſh of our Soul, let us conſider from the preſent Text, what ſin, and our heart riſings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God in afflictions, are, to wit, <hi>a charging of God fooliſhly.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Its, a charging, and a fooliſh charging.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, Its a <hi>charging of God;</hi> for with him we have to do in all conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Hee's the ſupreme; Men and Devi's work under him wickedly; but he works in and by them, holily and wiſely. Nor doth God barely permit, but commit ſuch and ſuch things to ſuch Inſtruments. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 22. 20, 22, 23. The matter ſtandeth not thus here, that the Devil moves for the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:135400:30" rendition="simple:additions"/> moleſting of <hi>Job,</hi> and ſo God ſigns the Petition, and gives way [at the Devils ſute] to the Devils deſign, and ther's an end of the buſineſs; but God, for holy ends, hath a purpoſe to afflict <hi>Job,</hi> and trie him to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt, and the Devils motions and machinations, ſucceed and ſerve that purpoſe <hi>Job</hi> 23. 14. We ought to ſpeak ſoberly of theſe things, but yet we may ſay truly, that when God hath a work to do, he accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dates himſelf with, and makes uſe of, what inſtruments he pleaſeth, and takes the doing of the thing to himſelf [2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. 12. <hi>I will do this]</hi> though the ſin in the acting be the inſtruments onely; what theſe do in a ſinfull, God doth in a penal, or probatory way, as here in <hi>Job.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Now, ſhall we riſe up and rage againſt God? 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 19. 27, 28.</p>
                     <p>Yet, How prone are we, in greater troubles and preſſures to ſay, <hi>Never any ſo troubled as I?</hi> We fret, we chaff; None abou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> us can pleaſe us; they that are neer us in relation, have little heart to come neer us. I beſeech you conſider what all this impatience amounts to, It is in true judgment, <hi>A drawing up of a charge against God;</hi> and, Is it fit <hi>(wee)</hi> ſhould charge <hi>[Him?]</hi> Our neer friends die, wee may call them our <hi>Gourd</hi> 
                        <note n="[a]" place="margin">Jona 4. 7, 8, 9.</note>, being a kind of guard to us againſt the heat and violence of worldly trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, theſe Gourds wither, and we are angry; Our ſoules are diſquieted, and we never ask why, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42. 11. but [perhaps] make as if we did well to be angry to the death, for our Gourd is withered, and the Sun beats on our heads. But, what made that Gourd to wither? Sure, ſome worm or other; But who prepared that worm? Is it not God? and is it not he alſo that prepares that vehement Eaſt winde, ſo that the ſun beats on our head, and we are ready to faint? Doth God indeed, do all this? and <hi>wilt thou condemn him that is most juſt?</hi> 
                        <note n="(b)" place="margin">Job. 34. 17.</note> Is He fit to be the object of our an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger? O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t hath Heaven cauſe to be angry with earth, but was earth ever juſtly angry with heaven? muſt we needs wound that Supreme and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty power, that cannot pervert judgment <note n="[c]" place="margin">Job 34. 12.</note>, through the ſides of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments and providences? How much better was <hi>David</hi>'s reverent reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution: <hi>I was dumb, I opened not my mouth, becauſe thou Lord didſt it.</hi> Pſal. 39. 9. I ſay, How much b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tter, and how much wiſer? For,</p>
                     <p>Secondly, This <hi>charging of God</hi> is a fooliſh thing, therefore <hi>Job</hi> ſaid to his wife tempting him to do ſo, <hi>Thou ſpeakeſt like one of the fooliſh women</hi> 
                        <note n="[d]" place="margin">Job. 2. 10.</note>.</p>
                     <p>The folly in it is manifeſt. For,</p>
                     <p n="1">1. The Charge is <hi>preſumptuous;</hi> He goes very high that opens his mouth againſt heaven <note n="[e]" place="margin">Pſal. 73. 9.</note>. Governors [they ſay] muſt be accountable; but it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they be men; God is greater than man, and gives no account of any of his matters <note n="[f]" place="margin">Job 33. 12, 13.</note>, He's far above all charges, and conteſtations.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Its <hi>Unrighteous;</hi> Its a charge that can never be made good, for God will not lay upon man more than is right, that he ſhould enter into Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with God. <hi>Job</hi> 34. 23. So, the folly of unrighteouſnes is added to the folly of preſumption.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. There is added to both, the folly of <hi>Selfe-ruine,</hi> while we wrangle with God out of ſelf-reſpects, ſuch preſumption, doubles, or trebles our affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; when <hi>Iſrael</hi> murmured after the deſtruct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>on of <hi>Korah,</hi> there dyed for that repining foureteen thouſand and ſeven hundred <hi>[Numb.</hi> 16. 41, 49.]
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:135400:31"/> beſide them that dyed about the matter of <hi>Korah,</hi> and this men get by their thwarting with God.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q.</hi> What's to be done then in the time of trouble, to prevent the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of our hearts againſt heaven?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> Find them a contrary work. Inſtead of charging God fooliſhly, let us <hi>charge our ſelves wiſely.</hi> 1 Sam. 22. 22. 2 Sam. 24. 10. 17. Say, I am the occaſion, I am the cauſe, God is juſt in it, God will bring good out of it <note n="(a)" place="margin">2 Sam. 16. 10, 12.</note>; ſay as that cruelly covetous, but at laſt penitent and well minded <hi>Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritius</hi> did, who when he was miſerably tortured himſelf, by <hi>Phocas</hi> (choſen Emperour in his room) and five of his ſons (together with his wife) were ſlain before his face, bore it with great patience, and often repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this ſaying, <hi>Juſt art thou Lord, and right is thy judgement</hi> 
                        <note n="(b)" place="margin">Func. comment. in Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nolog. l. 8.</note>.</p>
                     <p>But tho we ſhould charge our ſelves wiſely; Yet we may not <hi>overcharge our ſelves unwiſely.</hi> Say not (as ſome) O, God loves not me; nor am I any of his. I have made a profeſſion of religion, but had I had true goodnes, God would never have dealt ſo ſeverely with me. All this is but chaffy ſtuff; a medly made up of diſcontentednes and dejectednes; Imitate ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the confidence and magnanimity of this <hi>Job,</hi> who would never be got to let go his righteouſnes <note n="(c)" place="margin">Job 27. 6.</note>) and yeeld himſelf an hypocrite, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all his afflictions, and his friends hot and heavy diſputes againſt him, from that fair and ſpecious, but fallacious and falſe argument, <hi>Severely af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, therefore ſurely an Hypocrite.</hi> Bear not falſs witneſs againſt thy ſelf, nor add affliction to thine afflicted ſoul.</p>
                     <p>Having ſpoken thus much in the generality, let me crave leave to deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend a little lower, and to deſire you (with reſpect to the preſent occaſion) to ſuffer the words of exho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tation in theſe two particvlars.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Charge not God fooliſhly;</hi> when provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences be ſtrangely ſad either in<hi>—His ordinances, or His ſervants.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>1. Firſt, ſpeak not wild words, nor intertain unworthy thoughts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning any ordinance on which the Name of God is ſet. To be plain, Charge not prayer fooliſhly, (and therein, God) though they dye by cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples that are prayed for.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Beloved,</hi> It is not unknown to you, that for your deceaſed Paſtor that is now laid in his grave, and for his religious wife (dying a very little before h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m) I ſay, For theſe two faithfull and uſefull ſervants of God (in ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all for him), It is not unknown to you, that there was a time ſet apart for more ſolemn prayer; wherein God did ſeeme alſo to give in ſuch aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance as m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ght propheſy he would grant ſome deliverance <note n="(a)" place="margin">2 Chro. 12. 7.</note>, and ſay (at leaſt, in regard of the one or the other), <hi>This ſicknes is not unto death,</hi> John 11. 4. But it proves otherwiſe, and we ſeem to have loſt our Friends and our Prayers both. No wonder if for this our hearts be fild with ſorrow; but let us take heed (for all that) what we ſay; ſay any thing rather than this, that God is not the God that heareth prayer <note n="(b)" place="margin">Pſal. 65. 2.</note>, ſay any thing, ſay nothing rather than th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s, that it is to no purpoſe to pray <note n="(c)" place="margin">Mal. 3. 14.</note>, or that God ſaith to the houſe of <hi>Iſrael, Seek yee me in vain. Iſa.</hi> 45. 19.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q.</hi> What ſhall we ſay then?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A.</hi> 1 Say, that (your) ſin is great who had the benefit of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s labours
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:135400:31" rendition="simple:additions"/> (and made not a good uſe of that benefit) and that (our) ſin is great who prayed for his life, and its juſt that theſe ſins ſhould <hi>hide Gods face from us that he will not heare</hi> 
                        <note n="(d)" place="margin">Iſa. 59. 2.</note>.</p>
                     <p>2. Say, God is wiſe, He knows beſt what to do: we muſt not contend with him unleſs we will take upon us alſo to inſtruct him <note n="(e)" place="margin">Job 38. 2. &amp; 40. 2.</note>; we do but darken Gods counſels, and ſhew our own fooliſhnes, when we goe about to meaſure his dealing and diſpenſations by our ſhallow capacities.</p>
                     <p>3. Say, This wiſe God is reſolved on his way; Our prayers muſt not prevent his purpoſes, nor muſt we look to bring his decrees to our deſires. <hi>He is in one mind, and who can turn him? and what his ſoul deſireth even that he doth; for he performeth the thing that he hath appointed for every perſon, and many ſuch things are with him. Job</hi> 23. 13, 14.</p>
                     <p>4. We may miſtake our Enlargments, and have great reaſon (many times,) to be humbled in the review of them; For that room we find in our hearts, may haply ariſe from nature and natural parts; from a better temper of body at that time, or from better creatures received, quickning our natural abilities; And, if by ſuch aſſiſtances we be ſo rich <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n prayer that we want neither words nor matter, but yet pray too much in a way of human wiſdom (ſeeming in ſome ſort to contrive a way for God as beſt for him to walk in) and do not pray in the evidence and demonſtration of the Spirit, with due reſpect to Gods glory, and wiſedom and will; we can no more look to prevail (with) God, than they that preach after that man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner can look to prevail (for) him, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 4.</p>
                     <p>5. If we do not miſtake a <hi>Spiritful</hi> prayer for a <hi>Spiritual</hi> prayer, but our hearts be holily inlarged and powred forth before God, yet then, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther evil is apt to ariſe, and that is, a heart leſs humble after a prayer more high and heavenly; Many times we are dull and defective, and when wee travel in prayer, bring forth a leane deformed child, and then, it grieves us to look upon it; but when it is better with us, then, how apt are we to kiſs the beautiful child, to make too much of our performances, and the Babes we have brought forth (tho not without the grace of God in us) and too litle of Jeſus Chriſt, and the grace of God towards us; but God will not give his glory to another <note n="(a)" place="margin">Iſa. 48. 11.</note> 
                        <hi>[no not to his own grace]</hi> but make us know that though we have good things [by] our prayers, yet not [for] them.</p>
                     <p>6. And God may grant, <hi>denying;</hi> as our Saviour was <hi>heard in what he feared</hi> 
                        <note n="[a]" place="margin">Heb. 5. 7.</note>, though denyed in what he deſired, The cup paſſed not from <hi>(him),</hi> yet was he heard in that he paſſed from <hi>(it),</hi> not only undergoing, but outgrowing and overcomming all his ſufferings <note n="[b]" place="margin">Act. 2. 24.</note>.</p>
                     <p>So here, The things intended in prayer, and the arguments uſed in prayer for the life of your deceaſed Paſtor, were Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, the good of the Souls of this Congregation, the education of his great and little Family [great, becauſe ſo many, and little, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſo many of them ſo young] Now, If God will glorifie his Name otherwiſe (as we are ſure he will <hi>John</hi> 12. 28.) If God will provide well for the Congregation otherwiſe [as we hope he will, <hi>Numb.</hi> 27. 16, 17.] If God will raiſe aſſiſtance and ſubſiſtence for the Children left behind in
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:135400:32" rendition="simple:additions"/> another way (as we are perſuaded <note n="(c)" place="margin">2 King. 4. 1, 7.</note>, and begin to find he will) then are our <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nheard</hi> prayers <hi>Heard,</hi> and that the beſt way; our dear deceaſed Friends having their will in their much deſired happineſs; God having his will in their preſent death; and we having our will and deſire, though they be dead.</p>
                     <p>Now whereas in the laſt of theſe, that is, proviſion for ſo many mother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, and now fatherleſs children, there ſeemed to be the leaſt hope, yet God hath ſo wrought on the hearts of worthy and well affected perſons, that help is freely offered already for the education and diſpoſal of the moſt of them, which Chriſtian love, and moſt imitable charity (in theſe dayes wherein the condition of the families of many Miniſters is ſo hard and hazardous) puts me in mind of the ſweet words of our Saviour (wherein I conceive ſuch a comfort to be comprehended) <hi>He that leaves all for Chriſt, ſhall receive an hundred fold, now in this time, houſes and brethren and ſiſters and mothers, Mark</hi> 10. 30. <hi>and fathers too,</hi> for that's expreſs'd <hi>v.</hi> 29. If the Apoſtles left fathers, mothers, houſes, &amp;c. they had an hundred for one here; for every good Chriſtians houſe was their houſe (an hundred houſes for one) every old diſciple was a father to them, every Chriſtian matron, a mother. What our Saviour thus ſpeaks of the perſecution, we ſee verified in the diſſolution of his ſervants; They that had but one father and mother while their parents lived, have now many when they are gone, and by that means, the benefit both of maintenance and educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                     <p>Think well of prayer therefore while God works ſo well for thoſe that are prayed for, though by what hand he pleaſeth.</p>
                     <p>I ſhall conclude this with that ſavoury and comfortable ſaying of <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> 
                        <note n="(a)" place="margin">De conſid. ad Eugen um lib. 5. Mel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>us eſt Deum non inveniſſe quam non quaeſiviſſe.</note>.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Solus eſt Deus qui nunquam fruſtra quaeri poteſt, nec cum inveniri non poteſt. Its onely God</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that is never ſought in vain, no not then when he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be found. Let thy experience, O Eugenius,</hi> (for to him he writes) <hi>teach thee this, or, if it do not, believe him that hath tried it, I do not ſay, my ſelf, but that holy man of God that ſaith, The Lord is good</hi> (he doth not ſay, to the ſoul that findes him, but) <hi>to the ſoul that ſeeks him,</hi> Lament. 3. 25.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, Think well, not only of every Ordinance of God, but of every child of God; <hi>Charge not God fooliſhly in his ſervants</hi> (who are his <hi>Mal.</hi> 3. 17. and in whom he is charged, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 4. 5 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 74. 22.) no, though God ſtrike them heavily, and double his ſtroke; let none open their mouth and ſay, Here are two gone, the heads of the family, father and mother both, and that within a week together, and that leaving ſuch a charge behind them; ſhew me any that you call a profane family, Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in God hath made ſuch a ſpoil?</p>
                     <p>Unto whom it may ſuffice to ſay, If God bring ſuch evill on families that call upon his Name; ſhall they, who (too like the curſed families of Heathens that call not upon his Name <note n="(b)" place="margin">Jer. 10. 25.</note>) have no courſe nor care of Religion in their families; I ſay, <hi>ſhall they be unpuniſhed? they ſhall not be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſhed</hi> 
                        <note n="(c)" place="margin">Jer. 25. 29.</note>, God will ſurely meet with them one way or other, one day or other. Meanwhile, was it not a mercy that they died together unto whom
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:135400:32" rendition="simple:additions"/> it would have been ſo grievous to have lived aſunder? yea, that inſtead of living aſunder here, they live together in Heaven? Nor can we wonder at ſuch providences, if we do but look upon this <hi>Job</hi> (with whom we have now to do) who (not by a fever or any ordinary ſicknes, but) by an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary hand of God, and ſtroke of heaven, loſt at once all the children he had, even ſeven ſons, and three daughters, having nothing but a wife left him <note n="(a)" place="margin">Job 1. 2.</note>, that was a temptation <note n="(b)" place="margin">Job 2. 9.</note>, and affliction to him. <hi>Job</hi> 19. 17. Nor muſt <hi>Job</hi> for this be the worſe thought of, for men are not to be judg'd of by their condition but their cariage, And what <hi>Job</hi>'s cariage was we all know; Now, though I intend not any compariſon with him that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd ſo high a teſtimony from heaven, and that confirmed by the oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions and conqueſts of hell, yet if any ſhall liſt to make an unpartiall enquiry into theſe two perſons that made ſuch haſt one after another, it will, I doubt not, be found that they were ſuch as did truly fear God, as were careful of their duties in their places, very helpful to others according o their abilities of State and gifts, and who dwelt one with another a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to knowledge, and as heires together of the grace of life whereof they are now poſſeſs'd.</p>
                     <p>But, this being the day of his interring (whom God thought fit to take away laſt) it calls upon me to ſpeak of him ſomewhat more particularly; of whom (notwithſtanding) I ſhould not ſpeak further, were it not that the obſervation of what was good in him, may be good for us. I ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with what brevity I can preſent his example to you and to my ſelf, in theſe five things following.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. He was a <hi>Sound Orthodox Miniſter;</hi> And even that alone is very va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luable in theſe truth-deſerting-times. The Devill is a diſputing Devill, as we ſee by <hi>Michael</hi> the Archangel his opponent <note n="(d)" place="margin">Jude v. 9.</note>. Now in ſetled times (wherein the doctrine of Religion is better guarded by government,) he diſputes againſt holineſs, againſt the holy obſervation of the Lords day, and the neceſſity of a ſtrict walking with God, by all the arguments that profane men can pick up for that purpoſe; But in times more unſetled, eſpecially wherein Reformation is ſought (but not yet found) he uſes the wits of men to undermine &amp; oppoſe the Truth of God; but this our brother had learn'd the <hi>form of ſound words</hi> himſelf, and taught them others, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. 9.</p>
                     <p>It belongs to us Miniſters to minde this, for what are unſound Teachers? They are (to ſpeak as the Scripture ſpeaks) <hi>The Witches of the Church: O fooliſh Galatians, who hath bewitched you,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle <note n="(a)" place="margin">Gal. 3. 1.</note>? And who were thoſe Witches but the falſe Apoſtles by whom they were removed from the truth of the Goſpel <note n="(b)" place="margin">Gal. 1. 6, 7.</note>? If he that ſhould uncharm the ſorce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of others [as <hi>Luther</hi> ſpeaks on that place] be a witch himſelf, how dangerous is that Witchcraft? <hi>Matth.</hi> 6. 23.</p>
                     <p>And it much concerns you that are Hearers in this place to conſider whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you have received, and heard, and held faſt; Are not divers, in divers places (Some in this) turn'd aſide from the truth? Yea ſome of whom there was ſome reaſon to ſay, <hi>Will yee alſo go away</hi> 
                        <note n="[c]" place="margin">Joh. 6. 67</note>? O remember, Nothing is more odious than unſound and rotten hearers under ſound and right Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters.</p>
                     <p n="2">
                        <pb n="56" facs="tcp:135400:33" rendition="simple:additions"/> 2. He was a <hi>painful and faithful Miniſter,</hi> as all might ſee by his ready labours in Lectures abroad, and his conſtant imployment in his own place.</p>
                     <p>A Miniſter may be Orthodox, and yet idle; not unskilful and yet unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, but we, that are the Lords Watchmen, and the Shepheards of his ſheep, muſt know, that it concerns us to look about and labour for the good of ſouls, even as it concerns us to love Jeſus Chriſt; He ſpake but Scripture <note place="margin">Greg. de cura Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorali Pec. 1. c. 5.</note> that ſaid <hi>[Quiſquis virtutibus pollens, &amp;c.] He that being able is averſe from feeding the flock of God, is thereby convinc'd that he loves not the chief Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd, for it was he that ſaid to</hi> Peter, <hi>Loveſt thou me? then, feed my Sheep.</hi> John 21. 16, 17.</p>
                     <p>Whats a man able and appointed to teach, and yet careleſs and ſpeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, but [if we ſpeak in the language of Scripture] <hi>a dumb Dog?</hi> Iſa. 56. 10. that ſhould bark to drive away any thing harmful to the ſheep, but cannot bark <note n="(a)" place="margin">Iſa. 56. 10.</note> becauſe he w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ll not, and is ſilent becauſe aſleep. The <hi>blood of Souls ſhall be required at the hands of ſuch Shepherds, Ezek.</hi> 3. 18.</p>
                     <p>Meanwhile, do you [my beloved] you of this place, bethink your ſelves well in what ſtate you ſtand, no condition being more dangerous than that of unwarned men, that is, of men that wil not take warning under a Warning-giving Miniſter. In this caſe, the faithfull Paſtor hath <hi>deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered his ſoule,</hi> but the hearer that would not be warned ſhall <hi>periſh in his ſin. Exek.</hi> 3. 19, 21.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. He was a <hi>plain Preacher,</hi> that did not trouble his hearers with ſubtil and obſcure notions, with dark and uncouth expreſſions, ſuch as theſe proud and wanton times have produc'd, and theſe Manna-loth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ng t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mes have made much of.</p>
                     <p>Of ſuch <hi>Calvin</hi> makes great complaint, <hi>We ſee</hi> [ſaith he] <hi>even of thoſe that profeſſe the Goſpel, ſome that had rather be accounted ſubtil than ſincere, and ſublime than ſolid, when all their acutenes is meer childiſhnes, onely it pleaſes them well to be thought acute men, and by unskilful men they are applauded on that account. calv.</hi> in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 2.</p>
                     <p>For [as he ſaith elſwhere] <hi>thoſe ſpeculations that hold forth a ſubtilty of wit, the world hath ever preferd before ſolid doctrine, and ever will. Calv.</hi> in <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 22.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Pauls</hi> ſpeech and his preaching <note n="[b]" place="margin">1 Cor. 2. 4.</note> was not ſuch; nor will any man be ſuch who loves the ſaving, better than the pleaſing of his hearers. So far was that pious as well as profound <hi>Auguſtin</hi> from this hum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ur, as that he layes it down for a Rule <hi>[Plerun<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> conſuetudo Vulgaris utiſior eſt ſignificandis rebus quam integritas literata] Such expreſſions as are popular and customary, are better, for the moſt part, to make things known, than thoſe that (if we look to learning) are more compleat,</hi> whereupon, (citing that place <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139. 15. <hi>My ſubſtance,</hi> or (as he reads it) <hi>My bone is not h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>d from thee)</hi> he proteſſeth he had rather ſpeak babarouſly [and ſay, <hi>non eſt abſconditum à te oſſum meum</hi> 
                        <note n="[a]" place="margin">
                           <hi>Suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Reader did not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it were</hi> Os oſſis <hi>or</hi> Os oris.</note> 
                        <hi>quam ut ideò eſſet minus apertum quia magis Latinum eſt] than that there ſhould be more Latin and leſs light. Aug. de doctrina Chriſtiana, lib.</hi> 3.</p>
                     <p>Well were it if all Miniſters [eſpecially whom God hath placed among meaner people] were of that good mans mind, having the care he had to declare ſuffic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ency, and the conſcience that he had to reſolve upon perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuity;
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:135400:33" rendition="simple:additions"/> for what's an obſcure, and (by his people) unintelligible Paſtor, but an unkind father, that when the child askes bread, gives him a ſtone, a hard thing, which he knowes not what to make of, nor how to get nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment from. <hi>Luk</hi> 11. 11.</p>
                     <p>As for thoſe that have Teachers who come down to the capacity of their Hearers (which hath been and is your mercy here) Let them conſider, that if this work not upon them for the increaſe of knowledge and goodnes, it will one day witneſs againſt them, and be a great aggravation of their ſin, that their Prophets have not onely preached often, and <hi>multiplied viſions,</hi> but preach'd plainly, and <hi>uſed ſimilitudes</hi> 
                        <note n="(b)" place="margin">Hoſ. 12. 10.</note>, helping dimme eyes to the cleareſt light. Give me leave to ſay <hi>Beloved,</hi> Better for you have had a Miniſter that would have ſpoken <hi>Latin, Greek,</hi> or <hi>Hebrew</hi> to you, than one ſo willing to deale plainly with you, if you be not gainers, if God be not a gainer by that plaineſſe.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. He was a <hi>Powerfull Preacher,</hi> and one that ſweetly inſinuated him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf into the hearts of hearets, his doctrine dropping as the ſmall rain on the tender herbs <note n="(c)" place="margin">Deut. 32. 2.</note>. He was one that ſpake to the heart of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> 
                        <note n="(d)" place="margin">Iſa. 40. 2.</note>, an heart-affecting preacher, There lay his work and heart.</p>
                     <p>And whats a Preacher that delivers good things in a general way, but keeps off from the heart and conſcience, but like ſuch Phyſicians as give <hi>Catholique Pils</hi> that purge the belly, but never light on the particular pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant humour that moſt infeſts and endangers the body.</p>
                     <p>It concerns us Miniſters to conſider the diſeaſes and the conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of our charges, and accordingly apply our remedies, not ſhooting at <hi>Rovers</hi> but <hi>full-But</hi> againſt ſin; and in matter of comfort diſpenſing the grace of God that is given him with all faithfulnes and fitnes to them-ward over whom God hath ſet him <note n="(a)" place="margin">Epheſ. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</note>.</p>
                     <p>And for you that are hearers, Take account of your ſelves how you profit by two ſorts of Miniſters, 1. Such as mightily convince your underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, 2. Such as work on your affections and make your hearts to burne within you <hi>(b).</hi> Woe be to that man that keeps his errours under a ſound and convincing Miniſtry; or his luſts and ſins under an heart-ſtriking and conſcience-ſearching Miniſter. If God cloſe with thy conſcience, and thou ſtand out, God, and Miniſter, and Conſcience and all ſhall witneſs againſt thee at the laſt day.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. Laſtly, He was a <hi>Pious Miniſter,</hi> one whoſe life was ſuitable to his labours, and practice to his preaching.</p>
                     <p>Its a good life that puts life into a Miniſters preaching; Els, a good Preacher and a bad Liver, is like a boy that writes a faire copy, and blots it out with his ſlieve. People are to be fed with milk, but if Miniſters, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they have given a good meal, throw it all down with their foot, How ſhall poore hearers (whoſe eye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s not ſo much upon the work as the walk of the Miniſter) be nouriſhed with it?</p>
                     <p>Nor doth a good converſation give ſtrength to our doctrine, when it is delivered onely, but even to the deliverer it ſelf alſo. It is ſaid, <hi>Chriſt began both to do and teach,</hi> Act. 1. 1. <hi>Hierom</hi> gives this reaſon of the order, <hi>[Eru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beſcit</hi>
                        <pb n="58" facs="tcp:135400:34" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                        <hi>enim quamvis praeclara doctrina quam propria reprehendit conſcientia.</hi> Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron. ad princip. Virg.] <hi>Doing</hi> goes firſt, for, <hi>The check of a bad conſcience makes the best Sermon bluſh;</hi> But (as another ſayes) <hi>Nec conſcientia loquentem praepedit, cum vita linguam antecedit</hi> [<note n="a" place="margin">Greg. mor. in Job l. 6. c. 24.</note>]. <hi>A Miniſters conſcience will not check him, nor make his words ſtick in his teeth, when his life goes before his tongue,</hi> that is, when he preacheth that to others which men know before hand he hath practiſed himſelf.</p>
                     <p>Such a Paſtor hath no need to feare, but his people (I ſpeak to you of this Congregation) have ſo much the more need to feare, when a Miniſter is both a burning and a ſhining Lamp; burning by his doctrine, and ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning by his life and example. Remember that theſe join'd together, will either doe much good, or much hurt: Think ſadly of it whoever thou art that liveſt under a Miniſter (or Miniſters) in whom both theſe are; either they will be <hi>Loadſtones</hi> to draw thee, or <hi>Milſtones</hi> to drown thee.</p>
                     <p>I have now done, adding this onely in the concluſion, whatſoever in our deceaſed Brother ſavoured of human infirmities (for he had no doubt, his failings as well as other men) let that be buried with him: But as for thoſe good things which you ſaw in him, and knew to be in him, and now have heard of him, let them live in us.</p>
                     <p>The God of the ſpirits of all fleſh, that hath taken him to receive his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, ſettle here, a faithful, a fit, a fruitful man of God to ſucceed him in his work, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:135400:34"/>
                  <p>ANOTHER EXHORTATION DELIVERED <hi>JAN.</hi> 3. 1649.</p>
                  <p>At the interring of that ſingular ſervant of God, Mr. <hi>SAMUEL CROOK</hi> LATE PASTOR AT WRINGTON <hi>IN SOMERSETSHIRE, By a neighbour Miniſter, much in his company, and very much aſſiſted by his Miniſtry.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <figure/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. W.</hi> for <hi>John Place,</hi> and are to be Sold at his Shop at Furnivals Inn-Gate in <hi>Holburn.</hi> 1653.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_author">
                  <pb facs="tcp:135400:35"/>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:135400:35"/>
                  <head>The Letter of a worthy and Reverend Friend to the Author, relating to the enſuing exhortation.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have peruſed your <hi>Exhortation</hi> at Mr. <hi>Crook</hi>'s Funerall, and finde it grave and ſeaſonable: 'tis pity theſe <hi>Memorials</hi> ſhould be loſt &amp; condemn'd to an obſcure privacy, both for their own worth, and his ſake who was the occaſion of them. If my vote can do any thing with you, I ſhould deſire you to publiſh this exhortation with your Funerall Notes concerning <hi>Mr. Oliver,</hi> that both of them being <hi>burning and ſhining Lights</hi> in the ſame County and voyſinage, and in their places and dwellings not far aſunder, may live toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the ſame papers. Certainly, Gods <hi>Worthies</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve ſome publique <hi>Monument</hi> to continue their me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory and example, not onely for the imitation of the good, but that others by this ſolemn <hi>Teſtimony</hi> may know that once the Prophets and holy men of God have been amongſt them.</p>
                  <p>Wee learne from the Apoſtle, that <hi>dead</hi> Saints may yet ſpeak, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 4. that is, preach by their example, but then, there muſt be ſome to continue the memory of that example, or els, how ſhould it ſpeak ought of inſtruction to future Ages? therefore the Apoſtle ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveth of <hi>Abel</hi> in that place, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, he <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained witneſs that he was righteous.</hi> Which I referre
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:135400:36"/> to the publick witneſs and teſtimony of the Word, where his uſuall title and ſtile is <hi>righteous Abel;</hi> and he had before ſaid of all the Patriarchs verſ. 2. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>they obtained a good report,</hi> to wit, in the Church by the Scriptures: Now, ſince the <hi>Canon</hi> of faith was cloſed up, there is no reaſon the memorie of the Saints ſhould be loſt, and therefore God hath in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Age ſtirred up ſome that <hi>can handle the pen of the Writer,</hi> by ſome publique record to conſigne their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to the uſe of the Church: though I confeſs too many have been forgotten that were otherwiſe famous in their generations for want of care in this kind;</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Illachrymabili perierunt nocte,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Carent quia vate ſacro.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
                  <p>I add no more, but that I am</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your loving Brother, and fellow-labourer in the work of the Goſpel, <hi>THOMAS MANTON.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:135400:36"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>To the well-affected Reader, but more eſpecially, To my loving and reſpected Friends and Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, the Inhabitants of the Pariſh of</hi> Wrington <hi>in</hi> Somerſetſhire <hi>Grace, and Peace.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Ts eaſy to foreſee that a neceſſity lyes upon me to make ſome apologie for the celebrating of the Funerals of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters with ſuch (ſomething more than ordinary) ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity,</p>
                  <p>Wherein my defence is this,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That though the reaſon be not to magnifie <hi>the perſons of Miniſters,</hi> who ought ever to decreaſe in their fame and name, ſo that Chriſt may encreaſe <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 30.</note>, yet never was there more need to ſpeak for <hi>the Miniſtry</hi> than now, and to do right to the perſons of Miniſters with reſpect to the reputation of their calling. The Rule of the word is, <hi>Hold ſuch in reputation</hi> 
                     <note n="(b)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 29.</note>, but looking to the courſe of the World, we know that <hi>as concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this calling it is every where ſpoken againſt</hi> 
                     <note n="(c)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Act.</hi> 28. 22.</note>. Some ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity therefore there is to wipe away unjuſt and untrue aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions by a true relation of their worth who have had their ſhare in that contempt which <hi>in theſe ordinance-deſpiſing-dayes</hi> the Miniſters of Christ do every where lie under.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. It hath ever been the cuſtome of the Church of God in fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Orations, to recite, and afterward to write, the ſtory of the lives of eminent and wel-deſerving men, eſpecially of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and that upon great reaſon, as 1. To ſerve the will of God, whoſe mind it is that the memory of the juſt ſhould be bleſſed and be kept from rotting; And 2. To preſent ſuch as patterns to others, recommending therein the Apoſtles Rule, <hi>Be folowers</hi>
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:135400:37"/> 
                     <hi>together of me, and mark them which walk ſo as yee have us for an enſample</hi> 
                     <note n="(d)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 17.</note>.</p>
                  <p>And—</p>
                  <p n="3">3. (Which we may look upon as the higheſt thing) In this, Jeſus Chriſt himſelf hath gone before us, who was pleaſed to leave to all the world this teſtimony of his faithfull Forerunner, That <hi>he was a burning and a ſhining light</hi> 
                     <note n="(e)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 35.</note>; That <hi>he was a Prophet and more than a Prophet</hi> 
                     <note n="(f)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 11. 9.</note>. If Chriſt thought ſit to beare up their names that beare up his <note n="(g)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Act.</hi> 9. 15.</note>, I hope we ſhall not offend by walking in our Saviour's way.</p>
                  <p>4. But beſides all this, while I write to you the <hi>Inhabitants of the Town of Wrington,</hi> I muſt needs let you know that a principal reaſon of the firſt framing and preſent publiſhing of the enſuing <hi>exhortation,</hi> was, and is, to aſſiſt you in a profitable and perpetual remembrance of him that for ſo long time was your <hi>faithful Paſtor,</hi> and made it his work <hi>to guide you to true bleſſednes,</hi> for which purpoſe he wrote his <hi>excellent and moſt approved Catechiſm,</hi> That you might be grounded in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and followed it with continual preaching for your better pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency, and confirmed it by his Religious life, and perfected all by his holy and humble death; you (therefore) muſt be my Apology for publiſhing theſe unpoliſhed lines, wherein my purpoſe is not to ſet forth the full ſtory of <hi>Mr. Crook</hi>'s life, (that's written already by an exacter pen, and printed by it ſelf <note n="(h)" place="margin">
                        <hi>In a little book calld, The</hi> Life <hi>and</hi> Death <hi>of Mr.</hi> Samu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el Crook, <hi>by W. G.</hi>
                     </note>;) but my meaning is, a little more to inſiſt upon, and to draw down to particular uſe what is there wound up in a more general way; yet with ſome difference; for, the former things are of common concernment, and for the uſe of all men, eſpecially of Miniſters, unto whom it cannot but be profitable ſeriouſly to contemplate, and to propoſe unto themſelves, ſo imitable a <hi>patterne;</hi> But the later part is more eſpecially directed to <hi>your</hi> uſe, who were the daily Hearers of his ſound doctrine, and obſervers of his ſuitable converſation, and who are to be in ſpecial manner ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable for both. Think that <hi>He</hi> that hath been divers years dead, <hi>yet ſpeaks,</hi> and that in the Apoſtles language <note n="(i)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Act.</hi> 20. 31.</note>, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that by the ſpace of fourty ſeven years, I ceaſed not to warne every one of you with teares.</hi> And let theſe applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:135400:37" rendition="simple:additions"/> to your conſciences, which (when I had reſolv'd to have laid them aſide) Providence hath (by reiterated requeſts) a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> length produced, be an effectual meanes to rub up your memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and continually to aſſiſt and arme you againſt that fruit-hindring forgetfulneſs which is apt to ſeize even upon better people after their quickning Paſtors deceaſe; that ſo though you could not always have him <note n="(k)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi> 26. 11.</note>, yet you may <hi>after his deceaſe have thoſe things alwayes in remembrance that you heard from him</hi> 
                     <note n="(l)" place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 15.</note>. This will be an help to that which I would yet fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther exhort you to (as that which much concerns you) I mean, your profiting by your preſent Paſtor, whom God hath in much mercy ſent to you to confirme you by his diligent and dexterous preaching, and anſwerable living, in that word and way which you have formerly heard and ſeene from and in his pretious Predeceſſor. The benefit of all will redound to your ſelves, and be beſt ſeene <hi>in the day of Chriſt,</hi> when (they both) and all other Instructers that have truly deſired and ſought your ſpiritual good (amongſt whom reckon him if you pleaſe that now writes unto you) <hi>ſhall rejoyce that they have not run in vaine: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther laboured in vain</hi> 
                     <note n="(m)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 16.</note>; which that it may be your ſecurity, comfort, and honour at that great day, ſhall be the prayer of</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your truly welwiſhing Neighbour and ſervant in Chriſt Jeſus. W. T.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="exhortation">
                  <pb facs="tcp:135400:38"/>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:135400:38"/>
                  <head>AN EXHORTATION DELIVERED AT THE INTERRING OF Mr. SAMUEL CROOK, Late Paſtor of <hi>Wrington</hi> in <hi>Sommerſetſhire.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou have heard (honoured and beloved) ſo many good and grateful words already concerning this faithful ſervant of God <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                        <hi>In the ſtory of the life and death of Mr.</hi> Samuel Crook., <hi>printed An.</hi> 1641. <hi>you ſhall find them pag.</hi> 42. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> now interred, that I ſhall need to ſay the leſs; yet ſomething give me leave to add at the Funeral of ſo great an Inſtructer, and in ſo great a convention, for our fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inſtruction, wherein that I intend is, the edification of the living, though (for that reaſon) I ſhall be enforced to ſpeak divers things that will tend to the commendation of the dead; but what concerns <hi>him</hi> I ſhall endeavour to contract, and enlarge in that which may be uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to others.</p>
                  <p>In this our dear and reverend Brother and Father, all generally was <hi>good</hi> (I ſpeak not without conſideration and acknowledgement of human infirmity) and many things <hi>excellent,</hi> but <hi>four things</hi> exceeding <hi>rare</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. Firſt, that being of ſo excellent and acute parts and wit, he ſhould yet preach ſo plainly, popularly and profitably, and that from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:135400:39"/> of his Miniſtry, when ſuch abilities commonly fall either into <hi>obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> or <hi>vanity.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In former times the Church was troubled with learned obſcurity; much learning in many pulpits, but little light; ſtrong lines, but weak Sermons; In theſe later times, the Church is troubled againe with unlearned curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, appearing in new and affected words, uncouth and far-fetched no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, witty and verſatile paſſages and dictates, like the Oracles of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens <note n="(b)" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> that may be taken ſeveral wayes, but which way they ſhould be taken who can ſay? By this means it comes to paſs that it is hard for ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary people to know the meaning of the words, and when that's done, as hard to find the truth and ſoundneſs of the matter;</p>
                  <p>Thoſe old Sermons, ſtuft and puft up with human wiſedom and Authors, were (much) for oſtentation and admiration; Theſe now a dayes for recreation and their better content that have itching eares, but nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for edification, unto which obſcurity is a great enemy, and in a Preacher inconſiſtent with the Rule of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 4. as it is in an Orator with the rules of art <note n="†" place="margin">
                        <hi>In caeteris artibus id maximè excellit quod longiſſimè ſit ab imperitorum intelligentia ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> diſjunctum; in dicendo autem vitium vel maximum eſt à vulgari genere Oratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, at<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> à conſuetudine com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munis ſenſus abhorrere.</hi> Tul. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>de Orat.</hi>
                     </note>.</p>
                  <p>Happy they that can ſpeak as <hi>Paul</hi> did, as a Father, in the evidence and demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Spirit of God; and not as the <hi>Corinthian</hi> Teachers that were inſtructors, pedagogs, not Fathers <note n="(a)" place="margin">1 Cor. 4. 2.</note>, uſing the intiſing words of mans wiſdom to gain diſciples unto themſelves, when their duty was, in a way of plain and powerful preaching, to win ſouls to Jeſus Chriſt. Theſe Inſtructors and Schoolmaſters had many Scholars therefore, but it was <hi>Paul</hi> that had the children, and was the happy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of regeneration and ſalvation.</p>
                  <p>Our deceaſed Brother was ſuch a Father, plain and yet full of power in Gods Houſe, unto which I add, profitable alſo in his own Houſe and other mens;</p>
                  <p>And that I obſerve in him—</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Secondly, That being in ſo much company, yet he was very free from any unworthy words, from empty and impertinent diſcourſes. Many light things ſeem to weigh well enough in the ballances of Society, but his words in ſociety would hold weight in the ballance of the Sanctuary. Not that he was ever ſpeaking religiouſly, (yet often he ſpake of things religious and of them very obſervably) but ſtill he ſpake uſefully; he had (together with his piety) too much worth and ſufficiency to indure in himſelf tongue-vanity, So that what he ſpake was, though not ſtill good for every thing, yet good for ſomething.</p>
                  <p>O our idle words! How many houres ſpent in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany? &amp; in thoſe houres how much ſpoken? and yet when all comes to be ſummed up, we may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce ſadly of our words as <hi>Solomon</hi> did of the world, <hi>Vanity of Vanities, all's Vanity.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But this our deceaſed pattern was willing (divers times) rather to ſpeak nothing, than nothing to purpoſe.</p>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:135400:39"/>
                  <p> And his words were the better tempered, becauſe his heart and inner man was ſo little diſtempered.</p>
                  <p>For I cannot but ſpeak this in him,</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Thirdly, That on all occaſions and in all occurrences, (ſome where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of muſt needs give diſtaſt, bring in affliction, provoke to perturbation) yet he was ever obſerved to walk and beare up with much calmnes, and (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting the publique troubles of the Church of God in <hi>Germany</hi> and at home, which did indeed ſadden and wound his heart) with much cheerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of Spirit.</p>
                  <p>None further off from Stoicks than he in their denying affections, none more neere them than he in compoſing them; what they would nullifie, he did rectifie.</p>
                  <p>O that it could be ſaid, Hee and Wee! but how are our Faculties di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed, our Societies ſowred, yea prayers and holy exerciſes pudled with our imperious and impetuous paſſions?</p>
                  <p>As our Saviour ſometime ſaid, This did not <hi>Abraham:</hi> So may we truly ſay, It was not thus with our deceaſed Brother, whoſe Example therefore I am willing to preſent, not ſo much to adde to his honour whereof there is no ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d, but (whereof there is ſo great need) to our patience. Had it not been for this, I mean, that we have great need of the help of ſuch an example, I ſhould (in this and in other things) have ſuppreſd that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of him now he is dead, that was intolerable to him when he was alive: I have told you of his patience, onely in one thing (I confeſs) hee was impatient, I mean, in hearing thoſe things that ſeemed to ſet him up, and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d (indeed) advance him, above other men; which leads me to that that I would obſerve—</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Fourthly, to w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t his rare humility—well were it if we could ſpeak of our faults as he did when men ſpake of his vertues, that is, with weeping; for when any mentioned his perfections, it did but make him mind and mourn under the ſenſe of his imperfections. My ſelf viſiting him in his laſt ſicknes, and telling him of ſome that acknowledged themſelves to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted by his Miniſtry, he replyed with much relenting, O that God ſhould make me an inſtrument of ſo great a work. I have deſired to ſpend and be ſpent and to doe what good I could, but with weaknes, infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>And at the ſame time he declared that when others ſpake highly of <hi>Wrington,</hi> (for Chriſtans formerly did cry up ſound men as now they do u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſound) I never rejoyced in it (ſaid he) for I thought ſuch would not be of any long ſtanding.</p>
                  <p>O that we could think ſo meanly of our ſelves with our ſow things, with our nothings, as he did with his great things; and be ſo humble, with our two Talents as he was with his ten!</p>
                  <p>Having ſpoken thus much of him, (but for our uſe), Let us now reflect upon our ſelves, and conſider what a mercy we have enjoyed in enjoying him ſo long in theſe parts.</p>
                  <p>A mercy to us Miniſters; for that ſaying of one in the Univerſity which he was wont to mention, that Paſtors in the Countrey did <hi>dolare Lapides,</hi>
                     <pb n="70" facs="tcp:135400:40"/> Univerſity-Preachers did <hi>dolare Artifices,</hi> was very true of him (in the latter part of it) though a Countrey-Preacher. Know (Beloved) that all the Congregations hereabout, that have received good by our Miniſtry, have reaſon to bleſs God for <hi>Wrington-</hi>Miniſtry and him that was the guiding Paſtor here. Our Congregations have received much more good from us by the help that we received from him.</p>
                  <p>If his Miniſtry were a mercy to us and to our people round about, It was (ſure) a mercy to you of this place to whom his labours were peculiarly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, and it is to God that you are bound for it; For though the noble Patron were carefull to ſend and ſettle a faithfull Paſtor, yet how came one faithfull above many, to his hand? and who is it but God that thruſts forth labourers into his Vineyard?</p>
                  <p>Set your hearts (I beſeech you) to what your Saviour ſayes <note n="(a)" place="margin">Luk 4. 25.</note>, I tell you of a truth, there were many Widows in <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the dayes of <hi>Elijah,</hi> yet unto none of them was <hi>Elijah</hi> ſent but unto the Widow of <hi>Sarepta:</hi> So were there many aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>miſhed places and Pariſhes in the firſt dayes of this decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſervant of God, yet unto none was he ſent but to you; The more need have you to examin whether you have gotten by this meanes <note n="[b]" place="margin">1 King. 17. 15.</note> a barrell of meale that will not waſt, and a cruiſe of oil (I mean that Spiritual and Soul-ſupporting-ſuſtenance) that will not fail, and that will keep you from failing and periſhing.</p>
                  <p>But the ſame Saviour ſpeaks to you the ſecond time <note n="[c]" place="margin">Luk 4. 27.</note>, and ſayes, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Lepers were in Iſrael in the time of Elizeus the Prophet, and none of them was cleanſed ſaving Naaman the Syrian.</hi> How many Leprous ſoules in our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> yea Leprous Pariſhes? yet we may ſay (upon great reaſon) To none was ſuch an <hi>Eliſha</hi> ſent but to you. Now therefore examin; Is your Leproſte cleanſed? or, are <hi>Abana</hi> and <hi>Pharpar</hi> better to you than that <hi>Jordan,</hi> to which you have been directed? You are rich, worldly-wiſe, well thought of, &amp;c. but are you not Lepers? 2 <hi>King.</hi> 5. 1.</p>
                  <p>If I ſhould ſpeak more particularly to this Congregation, and thoſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to it, I would ſpeak a word,</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. To thoſe that did not hear this ever-ſpeaking Paſtor.</item>
                     <item>2. To thoſe that did.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>1. Firſt, to thoſe that did not hear him.] That did not hear him (may ſome ſay) were there any whoſe Underſtanding was ſo low, whoſe piety was ſo little, whoſe love was ſo cold, whoſe hearts, were ſo hard, as not to hear ſuch a Teacher?</p>
                  <p>You know (Beloved) whether there were not ſome ſuch here, and wee all know that there be many ſuch otherwhere; Unto whom I wiſh all good, they being heretofore (divers of them) hopefull Chriſtians, and not altogether hopeleſs now, as being men led and got away by tentation (for ſo in chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty we are willing to think) rather than go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> away out of their own diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition; Yet a word I have to ſay to them, and thats this <note n="(a)" place="margin">Gal. 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, 8.</note>, Ye did run well; who did hinder you? Doth any perſuade you to leave the Miniſtry that teacheth the truth of God? This perſuaſion cometh not from him that calleth you, but from them that trouble you, and ſour you and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce you, for <hi>A little Leven leveneth the whole lump:</hi> Conſult your own for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:135400:40"/> judgment; where the bleſſednes you ſpake of <note n="[b]" place="margin">Gal. 4 15.</note>? Once you thought your ſelves bleſſed in that Miniſtry which now you are ready to curſe and blaſpheme, and then you had not ſuch tentations to byaſs your judgment <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s now you have: Then you ſpake good words of the good Word of God in the mouth of his Miniſters, and you ſpake them (I think) out of the experience of that goodnes that the Miniſtry wrought in you, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort it brought unto you. How comes it to paſs that your judgment that was ſo well grounded, is ſo ſoon changed <note n="[c]" place="margin">Gal. 3. 1.</note>? conſult your future good, Can you underſtand Scripture without a guide <note n="[d]" place="margin">Act. 8. 31.</note>? be ſtable in truth and goodnes without a Nail <note n="[e]" place="margin">Eccle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 11.</note>? make ſpeed in the wayes of godlineſs without a <hi>Goad?</hi> (which Nailes are faſtned, and <hi>Goads</hi> uſed by the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Aſſemblies)—If you ſay you can, where's your humility? If you ſay you cannot, where's your wiſdom? If you ſpeak of all, and ſay, wee are no Miniſters, (as divers of you doe, not becauſe you have reaſon to ſay ſo, but becauſe you have need;) Then where's your truth? For, are not thoſe the Miniſters that God hath made Inſtruments to bring you (if you be brought) &amp; to bring many others that are brought unto Jeſus Chriſt? If any ſhall demand, may not they that are not right Miniſters be inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of converſion? I anſwer, If they may be ſo poſſibly; yet they are not ſo ordinarily. Is it probable that God would ever ſo honour a falſe and Antichriſtian Miniſtry, as when it plants and waters, to come in himſelf, and give ſo great and general ſucceſs to it as he hath done in <hi>England?</hi> Have any of you, have many of you, received true goodnes from us? (I mean from us, as workers with God and with whom God hath wrought) then, me thinks, you ſhould grant, that if we be not Apoſtles to others, if we be not Miniſters to others, yet (ſure) we are ſo to you; Remember the Apoſtles reaſoning, either Chriſt is in you, or you be reprobates, &amp; if Chriſt be in you, and you be not reprobates, then I truſt we are not reprobates <note n="[a]" place="margin">2 Cor. 13. 5, 6.</note>—If you be not reprobate Chriſtians, we are not reprobate Miniſters;—If the Apoſtle knew how to argue, you will not know how to anſwer.</p>
                  <p>Let me intreat you (therefore) by all the tokens of Chriſtian kindnes that have heretofore paſſed between us, yea, by all the bonds of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity wherein we have been heretofore United, to take ſo much care of your ſelves and ſoules as a little to reaſon the caſe with your own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences; Seriouſly and ſadly beſpeaking your ſelves in theſe or the like words, What if it ſhall prove at laſt that the Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> (of whom we have been the Hearers, but are now the ſlighters) be the faithfull Miniſters of God? what if it be found ſo at the day of Judgment? what if the Lord Jeſus Chriſt ſhall ſay, Such and ſuch a one was a burning and a ſhining lamp <note n="(b)" place="margin">Joh. 5. 35.</note>, and ye were willing for a ſeaſon to rejoyce in his light, and then ye run away, ſhook him of, and ſaid he had no light in him—If Jeſus Chriſt ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y thus (O Chriſtians) at that day (and its a thouſand to one he will ſay ſo) what will you ſay then? He tell you what you will ſay then (whatſoever you ſay now) to wit, juſt nothing <note n="[a]" place="margin">Mat. 22. 11.</note>; for what men have no reaſon to ſay now, They will have no face to ſay at the day of Judgment. And becauſe you will have nothing to ſay then, Give me leave to tell you what to ſay now;-O that God would give you hearts to ſay, This
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:135400:41"/> deceaſed and moſt ſinfully-deſerted-Paſtor ſhall be the laſt faithful Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter that ere I will refuſe to honour and eſteem very highly for his works ſake <note n="[b]" place="margin">1 Theſſ. 513.</note>, or refrain to hear; It is enough, and a great deal too much that I have deſpiſed the Miniſtry ſo long, and quarreled with the light till it be removed, but now I have done with this Undoing ſin <note n="(c)" place="margin">2 Chro. 36. 15, 16, 17.</note>, I abhor my ſelf for it, and all Miniſtry-contempt ſhall be buried in this grave, never to riſe again, but to be exchang'd for reverent thoughts of every holy man of God for time to come.—</p>
                  <p>Suffer me to add one word more, and to adviſe you (that your diſeaſes may be cured, and that you may be ſet right in the ſight of God) to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what you have received and heard, and hold faſt <note n="(d)" place="margin">Rev 3. 3.</note> and repent. Return to, and continue in, the things ye have learnd, knowing of whom ye have learned them <note n="[e]" place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 14.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> Why? wee have not learned them of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> That's true (we do with all humility acknowledge a great difference and diſtance) but know (though) of whom you have learned them; And here, though I ſhall ſeeme to ſpeak fondly, yet while that I ſay is ſaid at theſe Funerals, and reflects principally upon this deceaſed &amp; ever-reverenced Paſtor, I ſhall take the liberty to ſpeak freely, and again wiſh you ſeriouſly to conſider of whom you have learned that which you have formerly received-Not of ignorant men that knew not what they ſaid; Nor of vaine men that car'd not what they ſaid; Nor of Unfaithful men that would ſay any thing for their own advantage and advancement: but from men that have ſpent much that they might be able, and have ſpent themſelves when they were able to do all the good they could to your ſouls. Theſe things are ſpoken that you may hold faſt what you have, or at leaſt what you have had, not to lift up our ſelves, Tho we knew nothing by our ſelves, yet we are not thereby juſtified <note n="[a]" place="margin">1 Cor. 4. 4.</note>, but ſo much we hope may be ſaid truly of us as to make your contempt inexcuſable; leave (there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) that which cannot be juſtified, and in the fear of God Reſume that reverence of Gods Ordinances whereby they may be intertained for your healing and reducing firſt, for your walking wiſely in a perfect way <note n="[b]" place="margin">Pſal. 101. 2.</note> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and your comming to a happy journeys end at laſt.—Now</p>
                  <p>2. Secondly, For you of this congregation that were his conſtant Hearers, I have onely three words to ſay.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Firſt, examin your preſent temper, and compare it with what hath been formerly, and ſee whether God have not ſomwhat againſt you for loſs of your firſt love <note n="(c)" place="margin">Revel. 2. 4.</note>. Though a Miniſter do not loſe his firſt Hearers, yet his Hearers may loſe their firſt love, eſpecially, if it be not rightly laid; Enquire (therefore) whether it were the parts of the Preacher or the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of his preaching that hath affected your hearts. It was that of which He ſpake often, that a Miniſter of parts is unto people, as a very lovely ſong of one that hath a pleaſant voice and can play well on an Inſtrument <note n="[d]" place="margin">Ezek. 33. 32.</note>. The ſplendor of a Meſſenger (when he is in his full ſtrength) takes many, but happy they that be taken with the divinity <note n="(e)" place="margin">1 Cor. 14. 25.</note> of his Meſſage, and with the God that is in the Sermon; very like is their love to increaſe, ſince the longer a good Miniſter lives, the more of God lives in him and
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:135400:41"/> proceeds from him, eſpecially in publique and pulpit ſervice; and he growes more and more to be of <hi>John Baptiſts</hi> mind, that is, to carry the matter ſo in the courſe of his Miniſtry, that God may increaſe, though he decreaſe <note n="[a]" place="margin">Joh. 3 30.</note>. As this our deceaſed Brother did much reliſh that Scripture (when at a time it was, upon occaſion, recited to him) ſo did he much imitate that pattern. Search therefore whether your love hath increaſed with a God-increaſing Miniſtry. By this you may know the ſincerity of your love, for they that receive the Word into a good and honeſt heart, <note place="margin">[b] Luk 8. 15.</note> bring forth fruit with patience; the heat of their love being above that heat of the Sun and of perſecution that makes the ſtony ground to wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note n="[c]" place="margin">Mat. 13. 6. 21.</note>. Beloved Brethren, Theſe are the dayes wherein the love of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to the Miniſtry is waxen cold. I do not ſay happy We, but happy Ye, if your love be hot.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Secondly, Examin what your ſtate is, and how far the Lord Jeſus hath prevailed with you by ſuch a Miniſtry ſo long continued amongſt you. It was your faithfull Paſtors mind and motto, to ſpend and be ſpent, and that <note n="[d]" place="margin">2 Cor. 12. 15.</note> gladly, for he was ſtill obſerv'd to be ſad and mourning when (by infirmity or his lecture reſtraint) he could not be ſpending. Now why was this? what did he aim at in this? ſure, he ſought not Vours, but You <note n="[a]" place="margin">2 Cor. 12. 14.</note>.</p>
                  <p>And here, I ſhall gladly approve you of this Congregation for one thing; and crave leave to move a queſtion to you about another.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. This I muſt needs ſay is to be commended in you, that your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor had Yours, your <hi>Tithes,</hi> his <hi>Dues;</hi> for though <hi>Tithes</hi> be now an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefull word, yet obſerve, it is at the ſame time when the name of a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter is an ingratefull word alſo, and when the ſpirit of <hi>Julian</hi> the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtat is up again, on whom this brand lies, that he firſt invented the taking away of Tithes, that thereby he might not onely overthrow the Presbyters (which other perſecuting Emperours did) but the Presbytery and Miniſtry it ſelf, to wit, by withdrawing that which ſhould ſupport it. Not that we ſtand ſo much upon Tithes, as to urge abſolutely their Divine right, yet we think it lawfull to take them, and lawfull for others to pay them, yea (while an other maintenance is eſtabliſhed) a very unlawfull thing to detaine them, yea, moreover that there is never like to be found in this Nation any other way of maintenance equal in all points unto them for the fulfilling of Gods mind concerning his Miniſters maintenance; but that which now we ſtand upon is, a competent maintenance, which they that with-hold mouzell the mouth of the Ox that treads out the corn <note n="[a]" place="margin">1 Cor. 9. 9.</note>, fall into that crying ſin of keeping back the hire of the labourers <note n="[b]" place="margin">Jam. 5. 4.</note>, yea, they take a very effectuall courſe that the Lord of the Harveſt may have no labourers at all; Not becauſe Miniſters preach for a maintenance, but becauſe they are not able to preach, and ſupport themſelves in their cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and their Families, without it. Nor doe we ſpeak of theſe things out of diſtruſt; we ſay as <hi>Mordecai,</hi> maintenance for Gods faithfull Miniſters will come from another place <note n="(c)" place="margin">Heſt. 4. 14.</note>, but what comfort can they have that with-hold it, either for themſelves, or their Fathers houſes? Mean-while this may be your comfor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of this place, that you have been juſt and loving
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:135400:42"/> this way. A Miniſter ought to be a lover of hoſpitality <note n="[d]" place="margin">1 Tim. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 2.</note>, and ſo was (as all men know) the M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>niſter of this place; Beloved, I may ſay, you made him able to be ſo by doing him right in the matter of maintenance; I do not ſay, you made him willing, for he was moſt willing of himſelf, but you made him able, and found him willing. This I have ſpoken for your juſt commendation and others imitation. Now—</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Let me move unto you a queſtion, and the queſtion is this; He had Yours, but Had he You? can you ſay truly, My Miniſter had mine, and he had Me? for he that is worthy the name of a Miniſter ſeeks not ſheaves, but Souls: O Remember, the <hi>Corinthians</hi> firſt gave their own ſelves unto the Lord, and unto us (ſaith the Apoſtle) unto the Lord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Miniſters alſo by the will of God <note n="[a]" place="margin">2 Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 5.</note>, but mark, that's the method, firſt their own ſelves; In the obſerving of which Method your ſincere Paſter, who was for you a faithfull Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt, is an eminent pattern, who firſt ſpent himſelf for you, and then his eſtate amongſt you. Inquire (therefore) whether you be able to ſay he hath eſpouſed you to one Husband, that he might preſent you a chaſt Virgin to Jeſus Chriſt <note n="[b]" place="margin">2 Cor. 11. 2.</note>? Is the match between Chriſt and you made? Though he that marry a couple dye, yet, if they be well married alls well; their comfort continues. Happy you if your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor married you to Jeſus Chriſt, for though he be dead, yet Jeſus Chriſt and you do, and ſhall for ever live together. If any ſhall ſay, Another may marry me to Chriſt, though he have not; I anſwer, I will not deny that, yet all have not the ſame ſpirituall art, to manage the motion of mariage between Chriſt and a Chriſtian ſoul, and to perſuade the match. And I add further, Its very much if they that have con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>emned the motion for ſo many yeers paſt, have any heart to it for time to come. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe my purpoſe is onely to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oove all men to repent, and I would not leave any in a diſpairing cond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ion, therefore, I ſhall wiſh you,</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Thirdly and laſtly, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ink upon your duty for time to come. Let that ſad note and voice of your Saviour ſound in your eares,<hi>—And thou Capernaum which hast been exalted to heaven</hi> 
                     <note n="[c]" place="margin">Mat. 11. 23.</note>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I tremble to add the reſt; but do you that are in <hi>Capurnaums</hi> caſe lay it to heart and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent. O think, what? Hath the dew of grace by this Miniſtry wet ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne places and perſons round about, and Is my ſoul a dry and withered ſoul, and my heart a hard and ſtill-ſtony heart, who have liv'd ſo long <note place="margin">Gutta ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vat lapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem, &amp;c.</note> under the droppings of Gods Ordinances here?</p>
                  <p>O let my Paſtor being dead yet ſpeak, and let the bleſſed Spirit of God bring to my remembrance ſome of thoſe moving and ſoul-melting words of his that may yet work for my converſion and ſalvation! And for you that find your ſelves to have received good by this Miniſtry, keep it; yea, do not only keep your ſtock but increaſe it; what you receiv'd from him while he liv'd, ſtrive to improve (while you live) to the beſt uſe, imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Diſciples who remembred our Saviours words when they had loſt his preſence <note n="[a]" place="margin">John <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 22.</note>, and by that means ſtrengthened their faith. In ſpecial, Remember his Catechiſm (wherein he will ſtill live) ſtudy well that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent <hi>Guide.</hi> It ſpeaks every where a rare ſufficiency in him; let there be (by that help) a ſuitable proficiency in you.</p>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:135400:42"/>
                  <p> To Conclude, Duſt we are, and unto duſt we ſhall returne <note n="[b]" place="margin">Pſal. 90. 3.</note>, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween duſt and duſt is the ſeaſon to do our ſouls good; God help us to take it; and becauſe of the Uncertain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y of that return, to make haſt to take it. Teach us, O Lord ſo to number our dayes as to apply our hearts to wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom <note n="[c]" place="margin">Pſal. 90. 12.</note>, even that wiſdom, to be able to open immediatly <note n="[d]" place="margin">Luk 12. 36.</note> being (as far as may be) watchfull to do nothing which we would not be willing to be found doing, dying.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall add no more but what hath been already ſpoken, (for, How can we ſay leſs, and what can we ſay more?) <hi>My Father, my Father, the charet of Iſrael and the Horſemen thereof</hi> 
                     <note n="[e]" place="margin">2 King. 13. 14.</note>—O let this dear ſervant of God live in us, that we may (one day) live with him, and put on that crown which he hath, in part received, and which is in full, prepared for all that love the appearing of Jeſus Chriſt <note n="[f]" place="margin">2 Tim. 4. 8.</note>.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="errata">
                  <head>ERRATA.</head>
                  <p>PAge 5. line 20. for <hi>Woragton</hi> read <hi>Wrington,</hi> pag. 8. l. 14. for <hi>Corall</hi> read <hi>Corah,</hi> page 9. line firſt for dit read did, page 30. line 6. for <hi>ſimus paſtores</hi> read <hi>ſumus pictores,</hi> page 32. margent for <hi>Ibi</hi> read <hi>Ubi,</hi> for <hi>mercis</hi> read <hi>merces.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
